<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://softcom.ng/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://softcom.ng/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-12-04T11:13:50+01:00</updated><id>https://softcom.ng/</id><title type="html">Softcom Ltd</title><subtitle>Softcom builds software, products, and programs that connect people and businesses.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Softcom CIO, Tomi Amao speaks at TechCabal FinTech 2.0 summit</title><link href="https://softcom.ng/blog/tomi-speaks-at-tech-cabal/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Softcom CIO, Tomi Amao speaks at TechCabal FinTech 2.0 summit" /><published>2018-12-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-12-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://softcom.ng/blog/tomi-speaks-at-tech-cabal</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://softcom.ng/blog/tomi-speaks-at-tech-cabal/">&lt;p&gt;TechCabal, the online publication run by Big Cabal Media Limited–held a financial technology (fintech) town hall on Friday, November 30, 2018, at the Eyowo Studio in Ikeja GRA. Softcom Limited, makers of Eyowo–a payment and lifestyle solution sponsored the event themed “Fintech 2.0: Nigeria’s Fintech Future”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TechCabal’s FinTech 2.0 featured six familiar faces in the space as panellists. They are: CEO of Flutterwave–Olugbenga “GB” Agboola, Managing Director of Mines.io–Adia Sowho, Fintech Angel Investor–Yvonne Johnson, Academic Director at Lagos Business School–Dr Yinka David-West, Managing Director, Sankore Investments–Titi Odunfa-Adeoye and Chief Innovation Officer of Softcom Limited–Tomi Amao, as panelists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, employees of Transsnet Financial, a Chinese-owned FinTech company targeting Africans, attended the event–Sofia Zab, Head of Marketing and Steven Sun, Assistant General Manager.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transsnet Group is a joint venture between NetEase–a $30 billion Chinese internet company and Transsion group–makers of Africa’s most popular smartphone brands–Tecno, Infinix and iTel. Transsnet has now become the parent of Transsion’s media streaming service– Boomplay, mobile internet business–Afmobi, and its financial services company–Transsnet financial (makers of PalmPay, PalmCredit and PalmCoins). Continue reading about Transsion’s play in Africa especially their next frontier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sofia and Steven joined the room filled with 100+ people, as the audience engaged on the past, present and future of the financial services sector in Nigeria with a focus on FinTechs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/tech-cabal/tech-cabal-01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Audience engaged on the past, present and future of the financial services sector in Nigeria with a focus on FinTech&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a chronological run through of the highlights from the event. Particularly good for those who missed it, or those who would like a refresher. Let’s go!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-it-went-down-at-techcabals-fintech-20-town-hall&quot;&gt;How it went down at TechCabal’s FinTech 2.0 town hall&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doors were opened before the scheduled 10:00 am and early birds got a chance to do a pre-networking. Also, there was an Eyowo booth to the left, which led to the main area. At the Eyowo booth were Eyowo-branded ladies and gentlemen, standing around and showing the curious-early birds how Eyowo worked, occasionally sending them money. Occasionally because there was still going to be a demo session during the main event, per the agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few minutes past 11 am, Tomiwa Aladekomo–CEO, Big Cabal Media (BCM) and other members of the BCM team came to usher us into a room with about a 100 chairs (I forget the actual count, now), a podium covered in “Softcom Limited” wallpaper and a panel area for six right beside the podium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kick-off&quot;&gt;Kick-off&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/tech-cabal/tech-cabal-02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Timi Ajiboye of BuyCoins&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Timi Ajiboye of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.buycoins.io/&quot;&gt;BuyCoins&lt;/a&gt;, started the main event with a presentation on cryptocurrency and how they have done over a billion naira in trade in less than six months of launch. BuyCoins enables Nigerians to buy bitcoin and other digital currencies with their naira debit cards. He submitted that the best use case of cryptocurrency at the moment is in facilitating borderless transfers. I usually discourage people from seeing cryptocurrency as another get-rich-quick scheme,” Timi said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He added that there are new innovations towards mitigating the volatility of the digital currencies. Timi in particular asked a lot of questions during the session. Just as expected because the cryptocurrency market in Nigeria, is still in a state of flux as the regulators are yet to give a go on it. So, crypto innovators like Timi are jittery as to whether a statement from the CBN can blow their entire business out-the-water. However, the International Monetary Fund (IMF) has advised &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/business/2018/nov/14/imf-says-governments-could-set-up-their-own-cryptocurrencies&quot;&gt;central banks to set up their own cryptocurrencies&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/tech-cabal/tech-cabal-03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Emmanuel Mimshach Obioha, Program Manager at Ventures Platform&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thereafter, Emmanuel Mimshach Obioha, Program Manager at Ventures Platform, took the stage. He spoke on fintech opportunities in Nigeria and the offerings of Ventures Platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In partnership with ARM Investment, they have launched &lt;a href=&quot;https://azeria-labs.com/arm-lab-vm/&quot;&gt;Labs by ARM&lt;/a&gt; - a 12-week accelerator program for fintech startups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon came time for the demo we had all been waiting for, Softcom’s Chief Innovation Officer–Tomi Amao, mounted the stage and offered to send money to someone. All he needed was their phone number. He was there alongside one of Eyowo’s Product Managers–Ibinye Jamaica, who went to close to the volunteer to perform the Eyowo “magic”. For those familiar with mobile money, being able to send money to a phone number is not novel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was agitation in the room as more people wanted to receive the money, thankfully, they had registered for the event with their phone number, so Tomi had the Eyowo team disburse  1,000 naira to each person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomi’s demo signalled his introduction into presenting Eyowo to the captivated audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/tech-cabal/tech-cabal-04.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tomi Amao's Eyowo demo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In Nigeria, Banks have existed for 5 decades and mobile phones for barely 2 decades, yet, mobile phones have a deeper penetration”, reads page 3 of his Eyowo presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We looked at the low rate of successful transfers [citing POS failures amongst others] and decided that to make Eyowo work, we need to guarantee that transfers are successful 100% of the time,” Tomi said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make Eyowo accessible to everyone, Tomi said that they have introduced telephony banking in addition to USSD, SMS, web and app channels. For them, accessibility to one’s money is crucial whether the user was online or offline. Telephony banking, in this case, simply means a user can call a dedicated, automated support line and walk through the transactions they want to do. E.g buy airtime, transfer money to a bank or another phone number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-climax&quot;&gt;The climax&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To set the tone for the panel session, Bankole Oluwafemi, Co-founder of BCM and Techcabal’s Head of Content presented a draft of the FinTech industry report they are working on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/tech-cabal/tech-cabal-05.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bankole Oluwafemi, Co-founder of BCM and Techcabal’s Head of Content&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are highlights of the report:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Africa’s fintech industry is projected to be worth 14.5 trillion naira ($40 billion) by 2020&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2016 was the year of the FinTechs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As of December 2017, there were about 300 African fintech startups and 338 mobile money accounts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Between 2016-2018, fintech startups raised about $330 million (120.1 billion naira)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The panel session was moderated by the amiable Academic Director of the Lagos Business School, Dr Yinka David-West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/tech-cabal/tech-cabal-06.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Academic Director of the Lagos Business School, Dr Yinka David-West&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So many gems were dropped during the panel session. They also touched on the infamous &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.benjamindada.com/5-billion-psb-psp-mfb/&quot;&gt;Payment Service Banks Guidelines draft&lt;/a&gt; recently released by the Central Bank of Nigeria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Contrary to popular opinion, the N5 billion licencing fee is not a limitation. Rather, the CBN has made it easy for that young guy in Surulere to own a bank”, GB said. “It’s not like the fee is going from N0 - N5 billion, but it is being reduced from N20 billion [capital requirement of commercial banks] to N5 billion”. He concludes by saying, “The CBN is open to more innovation than most people think”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/tech-cabal/tech-cabal-07.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The panellists submitted that to achieve the financial inclusion target, money has to become digital&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the future of fintech, the panellists submitted that to achieve the financial inclusion target, money has to become digital. “For the future, money needs to become digital, to enable us to do all these things [e.g quicker cross-border transaction] that we’ve outlined,” said Tomi. “People need to trust digital money”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The biggest opportunity I see is in capital aggregation and financial literacy,” said Titi. “Let’s begin to look at all Wealthtech to solve the real problem Nigerians have which is poverty.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really, what purchasing power does the person living on less than a dollar (now N364) have? On his/her scale of preference, surviving comes before savings and investment. For such people, who are the bulk of the financially excluded, unbanked and underserved Nigerians, wealth creation is the financial service they need, she submits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/tech-cabal/tech-cabal-08.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A Panellist&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The panel concluded by saying, “we need to take off our Lagos lens. Lagos is not Nigeria. We need to look into solving the problem of poverty by unlocking agriculture”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other takeaways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Know the regulations and policies guiding the industry.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If your business doesn’t come directly under any of the regulations, abide by the ones covering aspects of your business. For example, if you do cryptocurrency, you have a digital wallet, there is a regulation for wallets–MMO regulation. So, abide by that first then go and engage the regulators&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Engage the regulators with leverage by showing them the value of your solution to the economy, as opposed to going off solely about the “innovativeness” of the tech&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There must be a balance with the Finance of “fin-tech” and technology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Uphold global standards vis-a-vis cybersecurity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leverage on partnerships and collaborations to scale and even to get an operating licence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/tech-cabal/tech-cabal-09.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Adia Sowho&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event was so enlightening that Adia Sowho voiced out that representatives of the regulators should be at such important stakeholder gatherings. We all nodded in agreement and went to grab snacks outside the main centre.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="FinTech" /><summary type="html">ITechCabal, the online publication run by Big Cabal Media Limited--held a financial technology (fintech) town hall on Friday, November 30</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Data: The Missing Piece for Effective Business Decision Making</title><link href="https://softcom.ng/blog/missing-piece/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Data: The Missing Piece for Effective Business Decision Making" /><published>2018-11-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-11-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://softcom.ng/blog/missing-piece</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://softcom.ng/blog/missing-piece/">&lt;p&gt;In recent times, there has been a microfocus on data in the technology industry and the global economy at large. More people are becoming aware of what it is, how it works and why it has become so important in our dealings. It is safe to say the rave is long overdue. Describing data in itself can be multi-faceted. The business dictionary defines data as ‘information in a raw or unorganized form (such as alphabets, numbers or symbols) that refer to or represent, conditions, ideas or objects.’ Wikipedia simply defines data as ‘facts and statistics collected together for reference or analysis’. Data is limitless and present everywhere in the universe and as such, it is important we learn how to use and properly manage it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data has been an essential part of human evolution for thousands of years. Human beings as a species are pattern solvers by default hence our need for data as a tool. In other words, we gather information about our surroundings to optimize our lives. The earliest humans passed on information only through word of mouth but as our brains developed, we began to see the need to record information. The first examples of this data preservation come from over 35,000 years ago with cave paintings. Most of the activities during this age were centered around hunting and gathering so it makes sense that the paintings were mostly of animals; a way to pass down knowledge of the types of animals to hunt and the weapons used for best results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recording information was a much more efficient way to pass down information and afforded us the chance to expand our knowledge-base rapidly, preserve the knowledge gained over generations and more importantly, presented us the opportunity to build on past knowledge to gain deeper insights on recurring issues or events. This accumulation of knowledge continued for thousands of years as our ancestors started to become more advanced developing more powerful tools and survival instincts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/missing-piece/missing-piece-01.png&quot; alt=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; title=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over time, human data collection moved beyond just information pertaining to survival. All across the world, history and stories began to be recorded more frequently primarily due to the fact that we became better at communicating ideas as spoken and written languages became more sophisticated. All the information since the cave paintings are but a small blip compared to the information currently at our fingertips. The worldwide adoption of mobile phones has sparked an exponential explosion in data creation and has been the catalyst for the field of Big Data to evolve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-big-data&quot;&gt;What is Big Data?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s not the amount of data that’s important. It’s what organizations do with the data that matters.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Big data can be analyzed for insights that lead to better decisions and strategic business moves. Nowadays, our issues have shifted from data production to utilizing these vast quantities of data. Big Data can be considered as the microscope used to peer into the world around us.  The significance of big data does not, in fact, revolve around how much data an organization has but what they can do with it. You can take data from any source, analyze it and yield answers that solve problems regarding cost optimization, time management, whether or not a new product should be developed and its most effective offerings and most relevant today, smart decision making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business-related tasks such as determining the root causes of failures, errors, and defects almost in real time; calculating entire risk portfolios in minutes and detecting fraudulent behavior even before it affects an organization, are all things that an organization can accomplish when big data and high-powered analytics are combined. Big data affects organizations across practically every industry. From banking to education, from the government to healthcare and manufacturing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;in-africa&quot;&gt;…In Africa&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;African history has always suffered from a limited number of written records. The 1960s, after most African countries had gained independence, served as the turning point for data gathering for African historians in Africa and elsewhere begin to borrow methods from archeology, linguistics, and oral history to investigate the continent’s rich and varied past. Information about Africa’s history (economic and otherwise) at this time was in high demand. Africa’s rapid economic growth rates during the late colonial and early postcolonial periods and the euphoria immediately following the independence raised new questions about the effects of imperialism and colonialism and the possibilities of future prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the data generated on the continent is still manual. The introduction of IoT tools and mechanism can automate the generation of data, making it available for easy analysis and less prone to mistakes. In Africa, such data is sometimes hard to come by since most companies haven’t fully automated their processes. Even those companies that are producing machine-readable data are not using the data effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, a couple of organizations in Africa are looking to take advantage of the vacuum in this space to produce applications that could solve problems plaguing the continent. Startups are taking advantage of Big Data and open data available on the continent and are changing lives as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bad data is costly.  With data driving so many decisions in our lives, the cost of bad data truly impacts us all, whether or not we realize it. IBM estimates that bad data costs the U.S. economy around $3.1 trillion dollars each year. The data that most businesses analyze is about their customers and if you’re relying on bad data, there is no way your business can succeed. Many companies have failed to maximize their potentials for lack of knowledge on how to store, enrich, analyze and monetize a huge volume of data they generate from their everyday operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/missing-piece/missing-piece-02.png&quot; alt=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; title=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that with this great access to information comes the equally great responsibility to guard such data. A data breach can occur when private/confidential information is intentionally or unintentionally released into an untrusted environment. Data breaches may involve financial information such as credit card or bank details, Personal Health Information (PHI), Personally Identifiable Information (PII), trade secrets of corporations or intellectual property. Most data breaches involve overexposed and vulnerable unstructured data – files, documents, and sensitive information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few days ago, a major data leak that involved personal and payment information relating to Arik Air passengers was &lt;a href=&quot;https://rainbowtabl.es/2018/10/30/arik-air/&quot; title=&quot;Placeholder&quot;&gt;exposed&lt;/a&gt;. The leak, which contained sensitive customer details such as device fingerprints, names, email addresses, last four digits of credit cards, and IP addresses, was discovered on September 6 by Justin Paine, the head of trust and safety at Cloudflare. Cloudflare is one of the largest internet security and cloud network platforms in the world. It will most probably involve investigation by authorities to get to the root of this as Arik Airline - initially believed to have been the culprit - has denied any wrongdoing in the matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consequences of such actions can be largely devastating to the parties involved. The Facebook-Cambridge Analytica from early this year was a major indicator of this. It was revealed that Cambridge Analytica, a company that had worked on Donald Trump’s US presidential election campaign, had harvested the personal data of millions of people’s Facebook profiles without their consent and used it for political purposes. It was described as a major turning point in the public understanding of personal data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this awakening came massive reforms on data laws. Europe is now covered by the world’s strongest data protection rules. The mutually agreed General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR) came into force on May 25, 2018, and was designed to modernize laws that protect the personal information of individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Africa, new &lt;a href=&quot;https://ww2.frost.com/news/press-releases/african-companies-beginning-find-value-big-data-finds-frost-sullivan/&quot; title=&quot;Placeholder&quot;&gt;analysis&lt;/a&gt; from data experts finds that most companies in Africa will still be learning how to utilise big data efficiently over the next few years. Addressing appropriate concerns, particularly the integration of the solution with other aspects of the business, will be critical to facilitating the effective implementation of a big data solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technological advancements at each stage of the big data value chain, notably the proliferation of connected devices such as sensors, will continue to drive the big data trend in Africa. Continued investments in network infrastructure and the ease of adoption of various analytics platforms will also contribute to the emergence of big data solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since big data is inextricably linked to two other technological trends – mobility and cloud – it is the combination of the three that will have the greatest impact in the market. Hence, telecommunications operators will play an increasingly important role in big data solutions as they look to leverage this tremendous opportunity in the African market.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Data Analytics" /><summary type="html">In recent times, there has been a microfocus on data in the technology industry and the global economy at large. More people are becoming aware of what it is, how it works and why it has become so important in our dealings.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Identity Management: Is IDaas the way forward?</title><link href="https://softcom.ng/blog/identity-management/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Identity Management: Is IDaas the way forward?" /><published>2018-11-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-11-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://softcom.ng/blog/identity-management</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://softcom.ng/blog/identity-management/">&lt;p&gt;Identity is a socially and historically constructed concept. We learn about our own identity and the identity of others through interactions with family, peers, organizations, institutions, media and other connections we make in our everyday life. Key facets of identity - like gender, social class, age, sexual orientation, race and ethnicity, religion, age, and disability - play significant roles in determining how we understand and experience the world, as well as shaping the types of opportunities and challenges we face. Social and cultural identity is also inextricably linked to issues of power, value systems, and ideology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the most basic level, however, identity refers to how people answer the question, “Who are you?”, a question that remains one of the most important questions that most people will ever face. We can ask it of ourselves and of others. In fact, We can face it as individuals and as members of social groups or categories. Sometimes, we may consider explicitly: “Who am I?”; “Who are we?”. And for as long as humanity has existed, we have adapted means of cultural, individual, and social identification `throughout history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The definition of identity also stems from its usage. Identity is any set of characteristics that define a person and can be used to uniquely identify that person. A person’s identity is made up of their own character combined with their family and social roots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The set of characteristics are decided by a legitimate issuing authority, most commonly federal or governments or their subsidiaries and any institutions, and may vary from one issuing authority to another. The purpose, though, is common throughout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/identity-mgt/identity-mgt-01.png&quot; alt=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; title=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-digital-identity&quot;&gt;WHAT IS DIGITAL IDENTITY?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several definitions of the term ‘digital identity’, from different perspectives, have appeared in several scholarly types of research. A simple definition is related to one of identity. Thus, identity is defined as a collection of data about a subject that represent attributes, preferences, and traits, so in parallel, in the digital world, a person’s identity is typically referred to as their digital identity. The term ‘digital identity’ has emerged through the evolution of the Internet. Wherever we go, we leave traces of fragmented information about our identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digital identity mechanisms offer the promise of greater efficiency, security, and trust across industries and entities. From the provision of financial services to the government-issued identification, digital identity enables transactions for the movement of people, funds, goods, data, and other resources. Just as instances of digital identity are fragmented, there are a number of different definitions for digital identity across human, legal entities and devices and “things” depending on context and industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digital identity is now often used in ways that require data about persons stored in computer systems to be linked to their civil, or national, identities. Furthermore, the use of digital identities is now so widespread that many discussions refer to “digital identity” as the entire collection of information generated by a person’s online activity. This includes usernames and passwords, online search activities, birth date, social security, and purchasing history. Especially where that information is publicly available and not anonymized, and can be used by others to discover that person’s civic identity. In this wider sense, a digital identity is a version, or facet, of a person’s social identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst the benefits of social identities means better usability (fewer passwords, login and registration steps, improved and easy support) and improved intelligence (which make it easier to use these OTT solutions), there are disadvantages concerning privacy or identity theft. This, in turn, is leading to hybrid models which link digital identities generated by service providers with the identities that users provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This need, together with the emergence of federated identity management, has given rise to complex scenarios in which identity management is carried out in a fragmented and adaptable way. This fragmentation means that now whoever issues and validates the credentials of a digital identity does not necessarily have to be the owner of the resource. This means being able to provide identity, as well as its management, as a service (IDaaS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/identity-mgt/identity-mgt-02.png&quot; alt=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; title=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;digital-identity-identity-as-a-service-idaas&quot;&gt;DIGITAL IDENTITY: IDENTITY AS A SERVICE (IDaaS)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decision to embrace Identity and Access Management as a Service (IDaaS), or cloud-based identity and access management, is a wise choice. IDaaS boosts the digital enterprise’s ability to address governance, employee satisfaction and IT operational efficiency issues while providing opportunities for enhanced agility and workforce productivity. The right IDaaS choice can cut operational costs, reduce risk and save time. However, choosing the ideal solution calls for careful consideration of several key elements: How deep is the provisioning? How easy is it to delegate? And how effectively does the solution accommodate the hybrid enterprise environment?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IDaaS solutions have been around for some time, but until recently, primarily focused on federated single sign-on (SSO) to SaaS applications. While federation for SaaS applications is a good first step for improving the user experience, large enterprises demand more mature solutions that can meet their requirements around security and compliance, and handle the complex challenges of hybrid environments that encompass both legacy on-premises applications as well as new SaaS applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IDaaS can play a key role in helping organizations reap the benefits of the hybrid enterprise environment. The right IDaaS solution can lead to the right balance among security, agility and user experience across the hybrid environment. And can provide the workforce with a consumer-grade user experience across on-premises and cloud-based applications: frictionless yet integrated. At the same time, an optimal IDaaS solution empowers the actual owners of the applications (often LOB owners) to move quickly and adopt the applications they need—without waiting for IT. Plus, app owners can easily and securely provide the necessary authentication, access, and entitlements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/identity-mgt/identity-mgt-03.png&quot; alt=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; title=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-idaas-helps&quot;&gt;HOW IDaaS HELPS&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the evolution of the Internet and its ever-increasing use by individuals, organizations are managing sensitive information of millions of individuals on an online basis. Access to such sensitive details has to be provided and controlled with the utmost efficiency while protecting and promoting individual privacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is more personal information out there than ever before, and most of it is controlled by others.
Increasingly people have little control over their own information. This is the real challenge facing organizations and governments in an era of exponential creation, networking and duplication of data, most of which is identifiable in nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Identification requirements are everywhere and increasing. Systems users have multiple identities which need to be managed. In the online digital environment identification demands are becoming more frequent. Increasingly, more and more granular information is being collected about individuals by third parties, and this data is being used in novel ways, for novel purposes – not all of which benefit the individual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While IDaaS solutions have come a long way in the past three to four years, they generally still lack the
broad and deep functionality of an on-premises IAM solution. Many cloud-based IAM solutions offer
federated SSO to a broad set of cloud apps and basic provisioning capabilities to only a small subset of
the apps. Many on-premises IAM capabilities are not supported with IDaaS, especially for legacy on-premises application integrations. Integration with any on-premises applications, if even possible, often requires difficult customization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The right IDaaS solution can provide a seamless, consumer-grade interface for users to access all apps, both on-premises and in the cloud. An IDaaS solution shouldn’t put all its emphasis on SaaS applications or positions password vaulting as an alternative to more-secure integrations with on-premises applications. Instead, the IDaaS solution should offer the ability to integrate with on-premises IAM solution to leverage existing investments and provide rapid time-to-value, without compromising security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ideal solution provides a true, built-in hybrid approach, with SSO to target SaaS and on-premises applications from a single launch pad. Regardless of whether the application is protected by IDaaS or the on-premises IAM systems, the user experience is seamless. This reduces the administrative burden and avoids duplication of effort in managing application access policies. The ideal IDaaS solution lets admins leverage existing on-premises IAM policies and dynamically evaluates policies, no matter where the applications live, to determine who should get access.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Data Analytics" /><summary type="html">Identity is a socially and historically constructed concept. We learn about our own identity and the identity of others through interactions with family, peers, organizations, institutions, media and other connections we make in our everyday life.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The N-Power programme is quietly taking many out of poverty</title><link href="https://softcom.ng/blog/npower-taking-away-poverty/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The N-Power programme is quietly taking many out of poverty" /><published>2018-10-23T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-10-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://softcom.ng/blog/npower-taking-away-poverty</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://softcom.ng/blog/npower-taking-away-poverty/">&lt;p&gt;The N-Power programme is quietly taking many out of poverty, writes Tochi Eze&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent my childhood in the company of poverty. My father, a civil servant at the time, had enough money to keep his family in a spacious flat at Ilasa and ensure that a driver took my sister and I to school in the mornings. Still, poverty sat in our living room, in the damp heat of the Lagos afternoon. Poverty ate our Garri and Ogbono; it gave its opinion on government and politics; it scolded us, and asked us to do our homework. It is hard to forget the many names and faces of the poverty of my childhood aunts; who called and always seemed to demand one thing or another. There seemed to be always one extra mouth to feed, one extra fee to pay, one dying person or business to save. Eventually, my father began to soak in the weight of these needs. He swelled from them, scraping off his resources and savings to measure up with his extended family messiah status, until poverty, once a far and distant thing that dwelt only with those around us finally became our own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, my family’s complicated relationship with poverty is not one to be assessed singularly. It mirrors wider socio-political realities. According to a 2010 &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nigerianstat.gov.ng/download/544&quot; title=&quot;report&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; by the National Bureau of Statistics, Nigeria has an alarming 60.9 % poverty ratio. These figures are not abstract numbers conjured out of thin air, they are embodied by millions of unemployed graduates, most of them on the fringes of an expanding global economy, lack marketable skills. This demography reflects what one of the greatest tragedies of the Nigerian state, and repeated failures of governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I stumbled on the story of a young woman called Hadiza from Bauchi State. Hadiza was an unemployed graduate of over six years who had taken to selling recharge cards to keep poverty outside the doors of her family. Entrepreneurial as she was, her efforts were abysmal, and the pressure to pay her bills and care for her aged parents began to spiral out of control. This was until she got into the N-Power programme, an initiative of the government’s National Social Investment Office and Job Creation Unit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The programme, which is domiciled in the office of the Vice-President, is many things at the same time; a skills acquisitions programme with 250 vocational training centres across the country, an internship and job creation effort that has so far engaged over 500,000 graduates from various disciplines and deployed them across the 36 states of the federation, and an attempt to increase the provision of services across four key sectors - health, education, agriculture and tax - to most parts of the country. All of these are glued together and driven by technology. N-Power graduate volunteers receive an internet-enabled Android device that trains them in a wide range of knowledge areas and helps them interact with community needs effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/out-of-poverty/nurse-woman.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Nurse&quot; title=&quot;Nurse woman&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initiatives like N-Power invite a more nuanced view of what we consider the encompassing failure of the governance structures in Nigeria. Many things are not working. Some things are. How can we get them to work better? What can we learn from their successes? And from my perspective, what dents are they making to the country’s worrying poverty statistics?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hadiza, now a trained teacher in Bauchi under N-Power, has received a monthly stipend of N30,000 for the last 11 months. If you understand the nature of poverty in Nigeria, you will understand that Hadiza’s gratitude to N-Power, and how far this sum has gone in loosening poverty’s grip and setting her on the journey to self-sustenance. There is a win-win element here worth underscoring; Hadiza receives a stipend, develops skill, her community gains a qualified teacher, and the society is a little relieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before Emmanuel joined N-Power in 2016 as an N-Agro volunteer, he was an Anthropology and Sociology graduate from Benue State University, struggling to make ends meet. In 2017 he was deployed, under the programme, to Benue State, to work with local farmers as an agriculture extension agent, a designation that puts him in touch with modern agricultural techniques, as well cutting-edge skills and knowledge in the sector. Today, Emmanuel’s ideas have become indispensable to the local farmers he interacts with, and also to himself who, utilizing the new knowledge gained in the agricultural sector, has launched a mid-sized poultry farm with the savings from his monthly stipends, and launched himself and his dependents out of poverty as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/out-of-poverty/man-in-farm.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Man in farm&quot; title=&quot;Man in farm&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is hard to go through the testimonies of these beneficiaries and not remember the faces of poverty from my growing years, the lives filled with aching need, the sometimes constant and entitled demands, and the burden of the provision that breadwinners and family patriarchs constantly have to bear. Emmanuel, before N-Power, too chased after favours from family members, requesting stipends for survival, small souvenirs of grace to meet his daily needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no overstating the importance of technology in tackling the complex socio-economic realities of the Nigerian experience. Yes, the cost for an ambitious project that aims to lift over 100 million people out of poverty is huge. But programmes like N-Power show how much leverage technology gives us to provide solutions at scale, and how central public-private partnerships are to achieving this; much like the National Social Investment Office and Job Creation Unit’s partnership with Softcom - an indigenous company with a global outlook, working in the private and public sectors to deliver transformational value using technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might seem overly ambitious for the N-Power programme to claim an outright answer or solution to the question of poverty in Nigeria. However, if all it does is take 500,000 people like Hadiza and Emmanuel out of the cycle of dependent youths, if it can propel them into self-actualization and empower them with resources and skills they need, if it can monitor and assess like the scheme has positioned itself to do, then maybe there is hope for the rest of Nigeria, nestled in homegrown initiatives leveraging on ubiquitous technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A version of this article appeared in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thisdaylive.com/index.php/2018/04/11/n-power-to-the-rescue/&quot; title=&quot;ThisDay&quot;&gt;ThisDay&lt;/a&gt; on April 11, 2018&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Social Impact" /><summary type="html">I spent my childhood in the company of poverty. My father, a civil servant at the time, had enough money to keep his family in a spacious flat at Ilasa and ensure that a driver took my sister and I to school in the mornings</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Finding techpreneurs in unlikely places</title><link href="https://softcom.ng/blog/finding-techpreneurs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Finding techpreneurs in unlikely places" /><published>2018-09-11T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-09-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://softcom.ng/blog/finding-techpreneurs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://softcom.ng/blog/finding-techpreneurs/">&lt;p&gt;In 2006, a group of women from Northern India tired of the growing rate of unreported crimes against women, domestic abuse cases and a patriarchal system of oppression, decided that taking matters into their own hands was the only way the quest for justice and possible change could be shortened. Regardless of the fear of hitting the serendipitous jackpot of martyrdom, the Gulabi Gang was formed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This group of women known by their pink saris (a symbol for strength) draped across their shoulders, and their adept skills in handling wooden weapons known as lathis (or sticks), are some of the unpopular heroes of our time; fighting daily for the social justice and human rights of all Indian women regardless of social status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only remembered the legend of the Gulabi Gang on a recent visit to a Maiduguri school facility, where I was present to contribute smart tablets equipped with an e-learning app designed by Softcom Limited – an innovative Nigerian tech solutions company. The mobile tablets come pre-programmed with reading and visual materials that cover the entire national curriculum - from Primary 1 through SS3 - for Nigerian children, alongside related content important for their holistic education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, my colleagues and I went on this trip with no expectations. I planned to distribute the tablets, work with my colleagues in training the teachers on the ground on how to navigate the app and bolster their training methods, pose for a few photos and head home. At the facility, however, my colleagues and I were greeted with the pleasant surprise of what I will refer to as the Nigerian version* of the Gulabi Gang.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/techpreneurs/techpreneurs-01.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; title=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Led by women who care less about amassing wealth with the intangible currency of public relations, they are evidently more keen on changing the lives of children displaced as a result of violence and conflict and bonded by a shared loss of loved ones. The promising future of this children - the one who could have become a big key distributor for a multinational FMCG conglomerate or the one who could have become an agrarian entrepreneur or the first female engineer from her tribe - had been temporarily truncated by situations the kids neither created, nor asked to be a part of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/techpreneurs/techpreneurs-02.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; title=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In helping these young minds on a journey to retrace their story of firsts, I met women (and men) who had taken on a cause to rebuild the lives of these disadvantaged young ones; guiding them on a journey of mental, physical, and social recovery, for the simple reason that no one else was doing so. I watched in awe as I saw children in hijabs and well (to the best of their ability) ironed button-downed uniforms being taught how to design little orange robots. I watched seemingly precariously, as kids no younger than 12, were taught the rudimentary basics of coding via a very intriguing board game called Robot Turtle. The final objective of this game is for these children to gradually become comfortable handling algorithms and ease them into general rules of coding over time. The long term goal behind this is to groom the minds of the children to eventually become very comfortable with code. If this training pattern is successful, several kids at this center will be able to handle code before their 15th birthday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/techpreneurs/techpreneurs-03.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; title=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intrigued by what I had just witnessed, I spent some time with my new Borno family, organizing a mini competition with some of the children; where the first to fully set up a simple light bulb circuit board wins a round. After several rounds of laughter and high energy, as groups of kids squealed in the delight of playful rivalry while trying to outdo each other, I watched in silence and smiled at the realization of how the journey of ‘firsts’ could still be achieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I raised a high-five to myself (in my mind of course), at this light bulb moment: imagining a time when some of the next generations of Nigerian techpreneurs were going to emerge from. A new crop of data scientists and software engineers that understand the need for social investment innovation through technology based on their own personal experiences. A new class of information technology experts able to develop solutions from an honest place of empathy, having lived through the harsh realities of the absence of these basic threads of humanity often taken for granted because of how knitted they are into the fabric of what we see as everyday life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is these young ones learning the basics of computer coding from an early age, understanding how easily accessible education could become, and how the current unconventional approaches to learning could open up more minds to brilliant and truly impactful ideas. In the words of Wole Soyinka: “The phenomenon of creativity, we know, is closely related to the ability to yoke together separate, and even seemingly incompatible, matrices. The fruits of creativity taste best when it comes from the least likely places.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/techpreneurs/techpreneurs-04.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; title=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/techpreneurs/techpreneurs-05.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; title=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The e-learning solution designed at Softcom hopefully also contributes to this tale of firsts. From changing our perception of what free education could look like, redefining what it could possibly mean for mobile money to finally break into the mainstream payment culture in Nigeria (similar to what M-pesa has done in Kenya), to providing profitable make money on the go platforms for anyone irrespective of location across Nigeria. with the least KYC requirements possible, be able to make at least $150 on a monthly basis without ever meeting their employers face to face. I cannot wait to read the New York Times best seller story of how a group of Africans through their own journey from hopelessness to a tale of firsts, changed the world.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Social Impact" /><summary type="html">In 2006, a group of women from Northern India tired of the growing rate of unreported crimes against women, domestic abuse cases and a patriarchal system of oppression, decided that taking matters into their own hands was the only way the quest for justice and possible change could be shortened.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is Africa Ready for a Smart Speaker Revolution?</title><link href="https://softcom.ng/blog/smart-speaker/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is Africa Ready for a Smart Speaker Revolution?" /><published>2018-08-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-08-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://softcom.ng/blog/smart-speaker</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://softcom.ng/blog/smart-speaker/">&lt;p&gt;In 2011, Siri - originally intended as a standalone iOS app - was introduced alongside the iPhone 4S in its beta version. With the release of Siri, Apple device owners could now send texts, emails, make appointments, search the web, just by talking to their phones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seven years ago, this new technology seemed exclusive to Apple device owners, but that is no longer the case. Tech firms have since been on the line to provide humans with their interpretation of voice-powered AIs; from Microsoft’s Cortana and Amazon’s Alexa. This is mainly due to the rapid pace at which virtual digital assistants are being used, and the increasing number of people who agree it is a part of their everyday lives. After all, the Virtual Digital Assistant (VDA) worldwide market size is currently &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statista.com/statistics/589079/worldwide-virtual-digital-assistants-consumer-market/&quot; title=&quot;estimated&quot;&gt;estimated&lt;/a&gt; at $5.21bn, a number set to be slightly under 2 billion people when projecting the number of digital assistant users worldwide by 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these beg some questions: Are digital assistants really that intelligent? Are they really that effective in performing tasks? What is the future of Natural Language Processing (NLP) - the form of artificial intelligence that helps technology interpret human language - in analyzing, and parsing voice output, and improving the current level of AI? How, or rather when is this technology going to be available for the African market?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the nature of intelligence, especially in the context of artificial intelligence is still a fairly complex topic, digital assistants have been able to achieve some level of success. They are used to perform routine tasks like making and receiving phone calls, checking weather forecasts, traffic updates, news, and even make personalized recommendations. As we move towards a more sustainable development model in the innovation process, it is important to consistently re-imagine the future of digital interactive actions in a world of internet-enabled, connected intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider Google Home - the brand of smart speakers developed by Google. Released globally in 2017, Google says you “control your smart home with your voice”, and even that may be a sophisticated way of describing it. Google Home is basically the Google Assistant, built into a speaker, aimed at making life easier for its users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google isn’t the first company to offer smart speakers to consumers despite recent studies showing that there are now 14 million Google Home units in U.S. homes. For example, the Amazon Echo was launched in 2015 and commands nearly 72% market share of current U.S smart speaker owners, according to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://voicebot.ai/2018/03/08/amazon-echo-maintains-large-market-share-lead-u-s-smart-speaker-user-base/&quot; title=&quot;Voicebot Smart Speaker Consumer Adoption Report&quot;&gt;Voicebot Smart Speaker Consumer Adoption Report&lt;/a&gt; published this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, with the pricing of the Google Home, the company has revitalized the artificial intelligence race. Overtime, the plan is to catch up due to their appeal to a wider income class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;an-african-narrative&quot;&gt;An African Narrative&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already, today, quite a number of smart speaker applications are being imagined for various markets. This is especially important in a market like Africa’s, where its digitally competent consumer base is distributed across the different income levels. Google also offers its smart speaker in 3 variants: Google Home, Google Home Mini, and Google Home Max - possibly in recognition of the different set of users the product is being sold to. While the Home Max is built for high quality indoor and outdoor audio output, the Home Mini offers a lesser priced option that can be easily adopted by Africa’s middle and low income class. It’s important to note that the Home Mini doesn’t compromise on quality, and is also packed with all the features of the digital assistant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, there are several challenges in Africa that a tech gadget like this can help solve. Take for instance in the area of health, where patient adherence remains a primary healthcare problem in Africa. A smart speaker can be set to remind patients of clinic appointments, when it’s time to take their drugs, and provide health tips. The health of many patients with cardiovascular diseases - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2014/10/africas-top-health-challenge-cardiovascular-disease/381699/&quot; title=&quot;a top health challenge in Africa&quot;&gt;a top health challenge in Africa&lt;/a&gt; - can also be improved by monitoring their hearts’ conditions continuously in such a way that the patient’s doctor is aware of a pending heart attack even before they feel the pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another sector smart speaker can help transform is the farming industry - especially in rural Africa. The continent is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fao.org/fileadmin/templates/wsfs/docs/expert_paper/How_to_Feed_the_World_in_2050.pdf&quot; title=&quot;projected&quot;&gt;projected&lt;/a&gt; to be home to about 2 billion people by 2050, which means farm productivity must accelerate at a faster rate than the global average to avoid continued mass hunger. A smart speaker could provide periodic notifications to monitor crop growth and enable farmers monitor deviations from normal growth. While it’s still common for farmers to plant according to the phases of the moon, they can get real time weather updates so as to know the best periods to plant certain crops. This can potentially improve farm productivity and reduce input waste by using analytics to facilitate data-driven farming practices for small-scale farmers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/smart-speaker/smart-speaker-01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A couple of people&quot; title=&quot;Love in the Air&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even designing the product to use local accents and dialects for easier understanding and acceptance by the market. Talking about use cases, one of the more popular functions of the smart speaker is its ability to provide up-to-date traffic reports. Imagine if in this part of the world, we commenced the use of smart speakers notifying users of mishap on preferred routes, as it affected the user’s already predefined Google calendar. This feature is called “proactive assistance”- a notification system for things which Google Home finds useful to the user. With the unpredictable nature of road traffic in Africa’s major cities, information readily available right before leaving the home could be the difference between being on time for appointments, or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, all of these is still conceptual. Most companies that build smart speakers still haven’t made them available here, with the general perception of the continent as a potential market still largely prevalent. However, with the new problem-solving solutions they can bring to Africa in general, smart speakers can be the next flag bearers of a technological revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2018, with solutions like these on offer, it’s no wonder we are witnessing a remarkable rise in the pervasiveness of smart speakers; one that is nearly unprecedented in the history of consumer electronics. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalpublicmedia.com/smart-audio-report/latest-report/&quot; title=&quot;Smart Audio report&quot;&gt;Smart Audio report&lt;/a&gt; found that 3/4 of all smart speaker owners have owned their device for less than one year, with the balance (26%) falling into the first adopters category. Perhaps there’s a current awareness of the multi-functional usefulness of these gadgets, the potential of connected devices, and the reasonable price at which they are offered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s crucial to note that the evolution of technology like smart speakers stem from a desire to be connected consistently to the Internet - which is true everywhere in the world. As a result of this, “The Internet of Things” (IoT) - a term used to describe the connection of everything from gadgets to ordinary objects, to the Internet, has become a piece of our culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it may not seem like the urgent need of the hour in Africa, understanding the capabilities of these devices make them appealing. With home automation and IoT poised to grow in the future, a piece of technology that make our lives easier is not a hard sell. The Google Home also largely delivers on primarily being an excellent digital assistant: it answers personalized questions, can access several internet services, and make hands-free phone calls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, the evolution of Wi-Fi-enabled smart devices means we have to deal with communicating with them. This means we can have conversations with them, the same way we talk to one another when we need to get things done. An effect of the Internet of Things is that smartphones will become not only our portal into this interconnected ecosystem, but a control to our lives: enabling access to information on the go, and completion of automated tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With more features including “visual responses” and a willingness to adapt their products and services for the non-American user, the Google Home has the potential of being the revolutionary device that changes the perception of IoT in Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like the earlier trends of mobile phones, laptops - and most recently wearable tech - the current rate of usage won’t remain low forever. In the not too distant future, Africans will be talking to home assistants that not only help with task-oriented commands, but also goal-oriented ones.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="AI" /><summary type="html">Are digital assistants really that intelligent? Are they really that effective in performing tasks? What is the future of Natural Language Processing (NLP) - the form of artificial intelligence that helps technology interpret human language - in analyzing, and parsing voice output, and improving the current level of AI?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How Africa Is Leveraging Tech To Drive Social Impact Programmes</title><link href="https://softcom.ng/blog/how-africa-is-leveraging-tech/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Africa Is Leveraging Tech To Drive Social Impact Programmes" /><published>2018-07-31T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-07-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://softcom.ng/blog/how-africa-is-leveraging-tech</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://softcom.ng/blog/how-africa-is-leveraging-tech/">&lt;p&gt;Over the past few years in Africa, there’s been a concerted effort towards creating social impact initiatives by the government, corporate organizations and even international non-government organizations (NGOs) in an attempt to reduce poverty and deliver a better standard of living for disadvantaged people and communities. With 47% of the African population battling extreme poverty, economic development policies targeted at improving the lives of the less privileged in the society have become much more important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, research suggests that things are not getting better as the level of poverty and marginalization appear to be on the increase in the continent. Africa remains by far the poorest continent on the planet — 28 of the world’s poorest countries are African.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several issues accompany the implementation of government policies, nevertheless, economic growth and development are addressed through the deployment of these policies. Issues such as inequality, economic diversification, unemployment, poverty, human capital deficit, rural development, are majorly solved through social impact programs. This makes the policymaking process as well as implementation — withstanding its challenges — highly imperative. On the whole, African social impact programs have continued to be held back by structural weaknesses — especially in the area of financial mobilization — that haven’t yet been tackled adequately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While much has been said about Africa’s struggle with corrupt leaders, and the role they play in the failure of these programs, there have been some success stories nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On March 18 2016, South Africa’s West Cape Province Departments of Social Development and Health committed 25 million rand ($1.62 million) to funding three social impact bonds (SIBs) for maternal and early childhood outcomes. It was the first ever funding committed by a middle-income government for an SIB, making South Africa’s choice to pioneer this new path encouraging. Over a period of three years, the goal has been to use “state funding to create a blended outcomes fund, which may prove more efficient than when non-profit organizations raise grant funding to augment inadequate government subsidies”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example is Mali’s Agricultural Competitiveness and Diversification Project (ACDP), implemented by the Malian Ministry of Agriculture aimed at poverty reduction and increase in rural incomes. The program has helped expand the market for mango and other crops, as well as build good business practices within the country’s agricultural sector. This has been achieved with some stakeholders — from farmers to harvesters to collectors to processors and exporters — all benefitting from the expansion in trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past 20 years however, the continent has recorded huge success in the mobile segment of Information and Communication Technologies (ICTs). Mobile networks have covered over 90% of Africa’s urban population, and Sub-Sahara has the highest ratio of mobile to telephone subscribers of any region in the world. There’s also been an increased awareness surrounding the central importance of education to development. The world today is a knowledge-based economy and the benefits accruable from the blurring geographical boundaries can only be maximised by nations with a highly skilled and educated labour force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Affordable education and easy access to information technology tools, thus, represents a means to foster economic development, as well as improve levels of education, especially in African countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/africa-leveraging-tech/africa-leveraging-tech-01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A couple of people&quot; title=&quot;Love in the Air&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nigeria’s N-Power
A social development program that combines technology and education is the N-Power program, launched by the current Nigerian government and chaired by Vice President, Yemi Osinbajo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;N-Power is a government initiative aimed at empowering Nigerian youths while achieving inclusion and productivity through large-scale skill development. It aims to improve the lives of 500,000 individuals over a two-year period, training them in programs that range from Health and Tax (N-Power Health and Tax) to Agriculture and Education (N-Power Agro and N-Power Teach).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eighteen months into the program, beneficiaries are expected to have created sustainable means of generating income at the nuclear and intra-community level given the access to skills and development courses provided via the e-learning platform that the program offers and the stipend provided by the government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it’s tempting to attribute the success of N-Power to the efficiency of its co-ordinators, an appreciation for the management of its IT infrastructure starts to emerge on a deeper glance; especially considering that the program in itself relies heavily on the use of ICTs. In offering beneficiaries an e-learning mobile tablet equipped with both offline and online study materials, the N-Power initiative is highly dependent on the technology that powers these devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this vein, the partnership between the federal government and Softcom, a private tech solutions company, highlights the best of what can be achieved when the public and private sector collaborates to implement policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Softcom Limited, we pride ourselves on delivering tech-based solutions to enable social and economic impact for the African continent. With industry expertise in different sectors, they’ve been able to connect individuals with meaningful innovations, from delivering the educational aspect of the N-Power platform on e-tablets to developing a truly inclusive FinTech solution. Softcom also engage in targeted community social responsibility campaigns built around tech, and aimed at impacting communities from the grassroots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The progressive biases looking for innovative ways to design and implement social impact programs becomes a model for African nations; understanding how and why economic recovery efforts work in other countries and adapting it for their own environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the perception of Africa as a struggling continent is to be changed, open regional economic collaboration and integration will be important to truly achieving economic diversification and inclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building solutions that work and delivering them in a country like Nigeria — with its myriad complexity — is a gargantuan task. With a population size that easily doubles that of over 70% of all African nations, it isn’t far-fetched to believe that the success of a development program in Nigeria could translate to success in most African countries.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Social Impact" /><summary type="html">Affordable education and easy access to information technology tools, represents a means to foster economic development, as well as improve levels of education, especially in African countries.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Choosing Home Series 2: Toluyemi talks about being a Woman in Tech</title><link href="https://softcom.ng/blog/choosing-home-series-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Choosing Home Series 2: Toluyemi talks about being a Woman in Tech" /><published>2018-07-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-07-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://softcom.ng/blog/choosing-home-series-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://softcom.ng/blog/choosing-home-series-2/">&lt;p&gt;As the perception continues to change on Africa’s one-dimensional portrayal as a struggling continent, the tide of brain drain from developing to developed nations is reducing as a growing number of highly skilled and educated Nigerians, Ghanaians, Somalians etc. flock back to their countries of birth after some time away. They left, either as children with their immigrant parents or for study and early career opportunities. They return, in search of an identity, of bigger opportunities, to seek their roots, and determined to make a change. The countries they come back to are certainly the winners in this affair, as these are typically the very best and brightest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/choosing-home-series-2/choosing-home-series-01.png&quot; alt=&quot;A couple of people&quot; title=&quot;Love in the Air&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toluyemi Nathaniel remembers when she had the awakening moment of making the decision to return home to Nigeria. It was close to the end of her 2-year stay in China studying for a Master’s Degree in International Economics and Business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For me, I just had to come back. I love Nigeria and I can’t imagine being somewhere else for so long without itching to return”, started a sprightly Tolu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“All I kept thinking of was how much can I change over there? I just feel sometimes, it’s more difficult to change things you haven’t experienced. Everyone that has made a change in this country are people that lived through the Nigerian story and made up their mind to change things when given the opportunity. I decided to join that group.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In substantiating her refreshing sense of duty towards her country, Tolu reveals that she wasn’t forced to return because her program was over — a common occurrence in some cases — but that she actually did have the chance to further her education there but declined to. It’s an obligation to national service that’s established subtly in all of how she talks about her return, but that can be missed from the affectionate way with which she describes China and the period of her stay there. Curious to understand how she found herself in China in the first place, I asked about the reasoning behind the decision to leave for that particular country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: Staying in a country with a different cultural background to what one is used to can be a bit tough, and while Nigerians travel to a lot of countries around the world, deciding to live in a country like China still sticks out as peculiar. Was it your choice to go to China or was it out of your control?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tolu:&lt;/strong&gt; Yes, deciding to go there was 100% my choice. It was actually my first time out of the country, but I didn’t want something familiar, which is what the UK or America would’ve been for me. In fact, immediately after I got there, there was this episode at the airport where there was a mix up with me reclaiming my luggage. Officials gathered trying to solve the problem, but they were all speaking Chinese, which I didn’t understand at the time. This didn’t frighten me, but instead did the opposite; I was, in fact, more interested to understand the language. In its own way for me, it was about fulfilling a sense of adventure I’d long craved. I’m a thrill seeker at heart, so China was a place I really looked forward to living in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/choosing-home-series-2/choosing-home-series-03.png&quot; alt=&quot;A couple of people&quot; title=&quot;Love in the Air&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her take on a seeming over-familiarization of foreigners with Western culture is valid in the growing sense that with its global connection, European culture has grown with an all-inclusive urge to adopt, adapt, and ultimately influence other cultural trends around the world. In comparison to a country with a rich cultural history and background still waiting to be explored by most, it’s understandable why the Asian country will be a better pick to experience an original cultural adventure. It’s all well and good, however, the intricacies of living as a minority in the most populated nation on earth remains a reality that can’t be written off. Last year, Quartz published a comprehensive report on a growing fear in some parts of China of a “black invasion bringing drugs and crime” due to the increasing number of African migrants. I talked to Tolu about what it’s like living as a black person in a foreign country, aware of recent victories for nationalist sentiments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: Can you share with us what it’s like studying and living in China as a young black Nigerian woman?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tolu:&lt;/strong&gt; That can honestly be a bit tricky to navigate because the Chinese aren’t used to seeing black people. They are almost fascinated when they see one, and still do things like rubbing a black person’s skin, asking if it is ‘dirt’. I’ve had a few people do that to me. Sometimes, they just stare at you because they’ve never seen someone like that before. In my case I was fortunate because Tianjin (where she stayed) has one of the highest percentages when it comes to the number of different national ethnicities. I met other Africans, and some of my classmates were in fact black. There are blatant cases like when cars don’t wait to pick you up, or when I was told to “sound American” at an interview trying to get a job as an English tutor on campus. So living there as an African woman, there’s this contention of you constantly trying to decide if it’s racism or simply ignorance which I guess is the same for most black people there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overt displays of racism from locals can be too much to handle for some living in the diaspora. For these people, the danger of being targeted by racial violence can be the deal breaker between settling and returning home. Tolu, however, insists that she doesn’t regret her decision to move there, and says she’s gained a new perspective on some issues because of some of her encounters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There’s a lot of how things are done over there that will be strange to us. There are things we can copy and a couple of things we shouldn’t copy. It’s a fascinating array of differences in culture and practice that if a balance can be found, a lot of problems will be solved. But the process of finding that balance comes with a firsthand participation in a challenging change to one’s conventions and ideas of the world.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case for diaspora-return driven development in Nigeria is compelling, and the advantages cannot be denied. Returnees come to represent a bridge of the ever-widening knowledge gap, finding solutions to knotty problems with more sophisticated approaches due to an experience of both worlds. With Nigeria’s labour force on a perpetual rise — &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vanguardngr.com/2017/12/nigerias-labour-force-increases-85m-q3-nbs/&quot; title=&quot;Love in the Air&quot;&gt;National Bureau of Statistics&lt;/a&gt; says it increased from 83.9m in Q2, 2017 to 85.1m in Q3, 2017 — the majority of the population being dominated by people who’ve gained some know-how in important areas of technology and systems will be key in furthering economic progress in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For her own part, Tolu works as an Admin and Procurement Associate at Softcom Ltd, a company which has the pungent line of “Engineering to enhance the way we live, learn and work in Africa” as part of its Solutions Portfolio. While the parallels are present, the difference in her educational background in Economics and Business and her current job role is still conspicuous. I tried to find out about how she found herself in this line of work, what the role entails, and what a typical day at work is like for her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: Can you explain a bit more about your role? What does working in Procurement/Operations mean in the tech world?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A:&lt;/strong&gt; Like I said earlier, I had the opportunity to start my PhD even after getting back to Nigeria but I declined because I wanted to work. When job opportunities in Business weren’t forthcoming, I took on the challenge of working in Admin &amp;amp; Procurement, a role I wasn’t so familiar with prior to that point. But it’s been amazing because I have learnt so much on the job and now I’m just working towards being the best I can be at it. In Admin, the objective is to ensure there is a smooth operation of activities in the office. Responsibilities can range from automating the monitoring of various activities and contracts to coordination and management of administrative issues like hygiene &amp;amp; welfare. Generally, admin is more concerned with making the work environment much more conducive to boost productivity levels. As a Procurement Associate, I’m equally tasked with being responsible for all the purchases at Softcom. In a tech company, this includes project-specific materials which involves negotiating with external vendors to secure advantageous terms. So in a way, my background in business has come in handy in executing some of my current job requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While trying to understand the complicated landscape of Nigeria’s job market, a bit of background context is required. The country is included among the 10 fastest growing markets in the world, but still faces the problem of an overcrowded labour market that’s made gainful employment a premium in recent years. Tech companies like Softcom meanwhile have taken advantage of the explosion of Nigeria’s digital economy, seeing the sector as an avenue to tap into a rapidly urbanizing population of about 80 million people, whilst providing solutions to issues and sustainable employment to citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important point of note is that Tolu talks about how the Nigerian job market remains a slippery slope to navigate for women, especially in tech. Despite extolling Softcom’svalue of commitment to diversity, she is under no illusions and is affirmatory when she answers “I honestly don’t think we are that much” to my question about how many women she thinks exists in tech spaces these days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gender disparity isn’t peculiar to the tech sector, but stats point to a decline in the percentage of women in computing-related occupations since 1991. It’s a problem felt across board, as women in tech still face significant barriers in the workplace; from a shortage of women role models to inequitable pay gap, to persistent gender bias that nearly 90% of them say they have experienced. I got a few of Tolu’s thoughts on what she thinks the future holds for women in tech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: How do you think we as a country can ensure there is more equitable pay across the board, how we get more women into senior level and executive positions, how we fight unconscious bias at all levels of a tech organization?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tolu:&lt;/strong&gt; I think we first of all need to create a nationwide awareness to change some long-held backward cultural beliefs about women, including that men are naturally more talented than women when it comes to tech. It starts when we are kids; I’d love to see more little girls in computer classes. They don’t have to all be doctors, lawyers, and engineers. An emphasis should also be placed on merit-based appointments. At Softcom, it doesn’t matter if you are male or female, if you bring value to the company, you’ll sit at the table. So it should be that it is one’s substance — not gender — that’s considered when deciding on delegating executive roles. The promotion of and donations to organizations dedicated to the cause of making workplaces as diverse as possible is also important in solving bias issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tolu imagines a bright future for women in tech and even for the industry at large. There’s a confidence in the idea that with the advancement of technology in coming years, there will be more job openings in tech. However, such is the optimism from new returnees that it can sometimes almost be misconstrued as wishful thinking. When asked about her message for those still struggling with the decision to come back home, she talks about “sobering realities” but insists there are revolutionary solutions waiting to be applied in several spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I can’t lie, it’s a bit tough. You can never be prepared for some things. The heat was almost unbearable for me initially. I also had a bad bout with cholera off the first glass of water I drank. So yes it can be rough but being strong and focusing on the motive for coming back keeps me going. For me, that is contributing daily towards being an agent of positive change in my country. I also have to add that for a young black woman, it can be extra difficult. The career ladder doesn’t favour us already but what I see it as are that these are the very dynamics that make the prospect of change appealing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no doubting the impact of diaspora returnees like Tolu and their contributions to the national effort of growth and development. The Nigerian government must develop credible strategies for progress in many of the areas that lead these people to leave their home countries in the first place. For those who have not decided to return home, they will never be motivated to contribute their energies to a national cause unless the government makes an effort at creating the type of country they would like to return to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Returning to the country with a strategic approach should also be encouraged among the returnees. Appreciating that there are visceral realities that come with living in Nigeria is key, but balancing that with the right, tolerant and optimistic attitude is important for their relocation to be successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above all, there should be a general understanding that there’s never been a better time than now for the application of great and progressive ideas in the country. In an emerging economy with strong numbers, opportunities abound that can shift the course of the nation onto a progressive path. Tolu recognizes the importance of opportunities when she talked about lessons she’s learnt over the past 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/choosing-home-series-2/choosing-home-series-03.png&quot; alt=&quot;Toluyemi Nathaniel&quot; title=&quot;Love in the Air&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If I was to write a letter to my younger self, it will be to take opportunities as they come. A Colombian friend in China used to tell me that “If you don’t taste the food, how do you know if you’ll like it?” A life lesson for me has really been that taking advantage of opportunities can unexpectedly change a lot in a short space of time.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="African Diaspora" /><category term="Women In Tech" /><summary type="html">The case for diaspora returnees and their contribution towards development is compelling. In the 2nd part of our Choosing Home series, Tolu Nathaniel talks about her experience in China and how she contributes to making an impact via Softcom.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Choosing Home: Young Nigerians Retracing Their Steps One Pace At a Time</title><link href="https://softcom.ng/blog/choosing-home/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Choosing Home: Young Nigerians Retracing Their Steps One Pace At a Time" /><published>2018-05-19T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-05-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://softcom.ng/blog/choosing-home</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://softcom.ng/blog/choosing-home/">&lt;p&gt;While marking Nigeria in the Diaspora day in 2015, Nigeria’s Foreign Affairs Minister at the time, Mrs. Ngozi Okonjo-Iweala observed that remittances by Nigerians in the Diaspora are in the region of $4 billion yearly. This will frankly be a staggering amount until you consider that just last year, the Senior Special Assistant to the President on Foreign Affairs and The Diaspora, Mrs Abike Dabiri-Erewa announced that about 15 million Nigerians live in the Diaspora.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These numbers should be rightly considered whopping sums that could — if properly applied — boost the economy of any developing country. However, there’s an increasingly new crop of returning Nigerians that are looking at making that impact on the upward curve of the economy with the application of their skills in the labour market, while simultaneously contributing to help build the Nigeria of their dreams. Data on the actual numbers of returnees is still lacking, but it is broadly acknowledged, based on the increasing visibility of the diaspora in society, that there has been a steady increase in returns in the past few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The raw energy of youth, a millennial generation, and the recent rise of many technology-powered companies in Nigeria are the common denominators present here. These companies try to address the country’s problems with their unique solutions. One of them that works at such a company is Ope Adeyemi, a Solutions Architect at Softcom Nigeria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not so surprisingly, Ope just returned last year after an almost 2-year stay in the United Kingdom during which he studied for a Master’s Degree in Control &amp;amp; Systems Engineering. The urge to bridge a knowledge gap and experience other cultures were on his mind when he left, but because his decision to willingly return will no doubt have come as a surprise to some Nigerians, I ask him about his thoughts on his return to the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: You’ve just moved back to the country in a move that will come as a surprise to majority of Nigerians active in the labour market, as there are a lot willing to at least try the opportunities they believe are more available abroad. Can you share the main motivation behind your decision to move back to the country?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ope: I got sponsored for a Masters Degree Program by a government body called Petroleum Technology Development Fund (PTDF). It was a very few of us picked out of a thousand of applicants after an exam. It was supposed to be a kind of implicit agreement between us and the government, to transfer the knowledge we gain the during the duration of the program back into the country. PTDF, however, wanted to make it official, so they demanded we sign a bond. Some objected to this initially, but for me, the question has always been that if the government is willing to invest about ₦50m on you, why wouldn’t you want to exchange that for an opportunity to apply some of those skills in contributing to the development of the country? For me even before going there, I took it is an obligation to come back and help in my way.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a degree of truth to the almost mythologized belief that Nigerians aren’t time conscious, but a factor for that might genuinely be — in the case of Lagos — due to the notorious traffic congestion the city’s infamous for. Lagos, Nigeria’s popular former capital, is its most populous state; which makes the astronomical high amount of internal revenue it generates on its own (the state governor puts Total Revenue Generated for 2017 at ₦503.7bn) not so surprising. Lagos is expected to gain from policy reforms focused on improving the support for private firms and has been touted to become the 2nd largest African city by Gross Domestic Product (GDP) according to an Oxford Economics report. By 2050, experts foresee that the country’s population is set to rocket to 397 million. While the population boom will impact the whole country, nowhere will it be more profound than in Lagos, putting it on the level of the world’s megacities but with less infrastructure than any other large cities of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, this increases pressure on the city’s job sector and accounts for the notoriously difficult to navigate setup of the Lagos labour market. Talking about getting situated and finding one’s feet in such a landscape, Ope reveals that in his own case, he had gotten the job at Softcom before he travellsed, and was still fortunate enough to be absorbed back into the fold on his return.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It has allowed me to continue my work with a sense of continuity and purpose that I probably wouldn’t have gotten anywhere else. The process of having the most qualified candidates get the jobs they deserve still needs a bit of fine-tuning, but I’m glad I get to work in the ICT industry because yes I love tech, but I’ve always primarily wondered how technology can help provide solutions to some long-standing problems.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2016, Nigeria recorded an all-time high contribution of 12.6% by ICT to its Gross Domestic Product and just last year, the Nigerian Communications Commission (NCC) announced that the quarterly contribution of ICT to the GDP has increased to ₦1.6trn from ₦1.4trn. This recent rise in the importance of ICT as a major contributor to the success of Nigeria’s economic diversification plan has birthed companies like Softcom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/choosing-home/choosing-home-01.png&quot; alt=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; title=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Softcom tags themselves as “a thinking company” and their solutions portfolio includes specialization in “creating and directing the implementation of strategic road maps that place organizations at the cusp of technology”. Ope agrees that Nigeria’s Information and Communication Technology industry can be a major factor in finally transitioning Nigeria’s economy from being less reliant on oil, but understanding exactly how might still be vague to a lot. I ask him about how his work at Softcom is helping to improve ICT’s position as a major tool for socio-economic development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: What are some of the more challenging but ultimately rewarding projects you’ve had an opportunity to take part in as a member of the staff at Softcom?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ope: I think they are 2 different things: challenging and impactful. A project might be challenging without being necessarily impactful, but I’m more interested in the latter. One of such projects was the MTN Trade Visibility Project. Basically, it was about the client needing an analysis on exactly which locations to prioritize their distribution of merchandize materials like chairs and banners among their retailers. The problem was that they weren’t getting any data needed for that. What we did at Softcom was to come up with a Trade Visibility analysis which entailed going around the country to gather information on MTN’s visibility against its competitors in certain areas. What this does is allow the client to optimally allocate resources to places where their presence is low as compared to competitors. The outcome of this project has driven down their expense by about 70%, which is objectively a whole lot. In this case, the project was challenging and very impactful at the same time.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The move of the world towards becoming a technology-driven society means the future of Information and Communications Technology is very promising in Nigeria. The ease of the networking process that involves brands and individuals is being constantly reimagined almost daily especially in the age of social media. A lot more people are also being made more aware of the changes good technology solutions can bring to present-day challenges in agriculture, health, education, banking and finance, and other areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Nigeria, this sense of a technology revolution and the progressive pace at which it’s currently growing makes the decision for people like Ope to return from the overseas and try to carve their way, not so far-fetched. On his work at Softcom aligning with the motivation behind his return to the country, he talks about how the ICT industry was the most obvious fit for the application of the knowledge he gained abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I studied Control &amp;amp; Systems Engineering for my Masters Program and while we could talk about the Oil &amp;amp; Gas industry, I had already been exposed in the tech industry prior to leaving, so it felt like a natural decision to come back and continue. Softcom’s different departments mean that the members of staff have ideas of how what they do aligns with their own individual goals. I currently work in a department called Client Services where I work as a Solutions Architect. Some of the things I do involves IT Solutions Designing, Business Development, and Brand Management. However, I specifically chose to come back to this role because I feel like while building the tech is the easy part, building the business around the tech is tricky.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The concept of Business Development has always interested me so this is my way of exploring the processes behind developing and implementing growth opportunities within and between organizations.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/choosing-home/choosing-home-02.png&quot; alt=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi discussing why he came back to Nigeria.&quot; title=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi discussing why he came back to Nigeria.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea behind Nigerians in the Diaspora, now established as a euphemism for Nigerians living outside the country, particularly in Europe and America, is fascinating. Nevertheless, lanes should be opened for youths skilled or educated in the West to return and contribute towards the process of achieving real growth in the country. The drive and resourcefulness of people like Ope in different sectors of the country is important as Nigeria moves towards becoming a globally competitive nation. Questions surrounding how experience gained by these Nigerians can be harnessed for the direct benefit of the country needs to be asked, alongside awareness campaigns spreading word of the opportunities that are beginning to spring up in the country.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="African Diaspora" /><summary type="html">The idea behind Nigerians in the Diaspora, now established as a euphemism for Nigerians living outside the country, particularly in Europe and America, is fascinating. Read about the reason behind Ope Adeyemi’s decision to return to Nigeria, after an almost 2-year stay in the United Kingdom.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Facial Recognition: What It Is and How Organisations Can Benefit</title><link href="https://softcom.ng/blog/facial-recognition/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Facial Recognition: What It Is and How Organisations Can Benefit" /><published>2018-04-13T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-04-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://softcom.ng/blog/facial-recognition</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://softcom.ng/blog/facial-recognition/">&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, we are observing more cameras in our society. They are present in quite a lot of places: streets, supermarkets, churches, mosques and many other public places across Nigeria. The primary aim of their presence is most of the time related to surveillance and security management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Facial recognition being one of the blow-the-trumpet features to come to smart devices and with the IPhone X gaining quite some popularity amongst phone users in Nigeria, FR technology is definitely here to positively disrupt the process of achieving identity management and even payment in the Nigerian fin-tech space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-does-fr-actually-work&quot;&gt;How Does FR Actually work?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FR algorithms simply extract facial information from a person’s face and analyses these features against a set of rules previously set up within the algorithm. The most popular face recognition method (Three-Dimensional Recognition) uses 3D sensors to determine certain facial information — face structure, chin, nose and eye sockets and compares it against a previously saved copy of the image on a phone or a database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/facial-recognition/facial-recognition-01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Placeholder&quot; title=&quot;Placeholder&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, Apple’s Face ID on the iPhone X “uses a ‘TrueDepth’ camera setup, which blasts your face with more than 30,000 infrared dots and scans your face in 3D. A portion of the A11 Bionic chip’s neural engine transforms the depth map and infrared image into a mathematical representation and compares that representation to the enrolled facial data.” This method helps the smartphone make a quick decision on if the person holding the phone to his or her face truly owns the phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Access Management:&lt;/strong&gt; With facial recognition, organizations can easily manage entrance and exit at their business locations, achieve optimum staff identity management, attendance monitoring and surveillance on business premises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;your-cameras-are-becoming-part-of-your-marketing-team&quot;&gt;Your cameras are becoming part of your Marketing Team&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Large retail businesses can access insightful customer information by capturing the facial data of customers that visit their stores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Analytics:&lt;/strong&gt; For example, a shopper goes to ShopRite, Maryland Mall and makes several purchases of a specific brand of chocolate over the course of 1 month. ShopRite can store these vital biometric information which may give quite some insight into a customer’s in-store purchasing behaviour, demographics, psychographics etc. With access to this type of data, businesses can make more informed marketing decisions like simply offering him discount on many purchases of his favourite chocolate or presenting him with loyalty schemes etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/facial-recognition/facial-recognition-02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Placeholder&quot; title=&quot;Placeholder&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identity Management:&lt;/strong&gt; Examination bodies like UTME, IELTS and TOEFL can also utilize facial recognition in managing various attendees’ identity in physical or online examinations. FR can also be used in checking travelers at airports and boarding stations.In the United States, the Transportation Security Administration (TSA) recently launched a facial check-in feature at airports.This was piloted a few weeks ago at the Los Angeles LAX airport. With this feature, travelers can literally walk the check-in aisle and get checked-in via facial recognition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between January and September 2017, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.premiumtimesng.com/business/business-news/253834-nigerian-airports-record-9-2-million-passengers-140552-aircraft-movement-nine-months.html&quot; title=&quot;Placeholder&quot;&gt;Nigeria’s airports&lt;/a&gt; recorded 9.2 million flights in 140,552 aircraft movements . With this high amount of travellers flying within and outside Nigeria, an investment in FR technology by Nigeria’s NCAA, FAAN will ensure a seamless check-in and boarding process at all airports in Nigeria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;are-we-amped-about-what-were-building-yes&quot;&gt;Are We Amped About What We’re Building? Yes!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building solutions that add value to people and businesses is an important part of the things we do at Softcom. In the coming weeks, we’ll be launching one of our fin-tech products aimed at helping our potential users achieve seamless payments via their telephone numbers and more importantly approving payments via facial recognition. With the FR algorithm, users can easily achieve payments by simply placing their mobile devices against their faces to authorize payments at a brick and mortar shopping store or online when.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="AI" /><summary type="html">With facial recognition being one of the blow-the-trumpet features to come to smart devices, FR technology is definitely here to positively disrupt the process of achieving identity management and even payment in the Nigerian Fin-Tech space.</summary></entry></feed>