<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://softcom.ng/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://softcom.ng/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-09-20T13:36:47+01:00</updated><id>https://softcom.ng/</id><title type="html">Softcom Ltd</title><subtitle>Softcom builds software, products, and programs that connect people and businesses.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Finding techpreneurs in unlikely places</title><link href="https://softcom.ng/blog/finding-techpreneurs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Finding techpreneurs in unlikely places" /><published>2018-09-11T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-09-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://softcom.ng/blog/finding-techpreneurs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://softcom.ng/blog/finding-techpreneurs/">&lt;p&gt;In 2006, a group of women from Northern India tired of the growing rate of unreported crimes against women, domestic abuse cases and a patriarchal system of oppression, decided that taking matters into their own hands was the only way the quest for justice and possible change could be shortened. Regardless of the fear of hitting the serendipitous jackpot of martyrdom, the Gulabi Gang was formed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This group of women known by their pink saris (a symbol for strength) draped across their shoulders, and their adept skills in handling wooden weapons known as lathis (or sticks), are some of the unpopular heroes of our time; fighting daily for the social justice and human rights of all Indian women regardless of social status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only remembered the legend of the Gulabi Gang on a recent visit to a Maiduguri school facility, where I was present to contribute smart tablets equipped with an e-learning app designed by Softcom Limited – an innovative Nigerian tech solutions company. The mobile tablets come pre-programmed with reading and visual materials that cover the entire national curriculum - from Primary 1 through SS3 - for Nigerian children, alongside related content important for their holistic education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, my colleagues and I went on this trip with no expectations. I planned to distribute the tablets, work with my colleagues in training the teachers on the ground on how to navigate the app and bolster their training methods, pose for a few photos and head home. At the facility, however, my colleagues and I were greeted with the pleasant surprise of what I will refer to as the Nigerian version* of the Gulabi Gang.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/techpreneurs/techpreneurs-01.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; title=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Led by women who care less about amassing wealth with the intangible currency of public relations, they are evidently more keen on changing the lives of children displaced as a result of violence and conflict and bonded by a shared loss of loved ones. The promising future of this children - the one who could have become a big key distributor for a multinational FMCG conglomerate or the one who could have become an agrarian entrepreneur or the first female engineer from her tribe - had been temporarily truncated by situations the kids neither created, nor asked to be a part of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/techpreneurs/techpreneurs-02.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; title=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In helping these young minds on a journey to retrace their story of firsts, I met women (and men) who had taken on a cause to rebuild the lives of these disadvantaged young ones; guiding them on a journey of mental, physical, and social recovery, for the simple reason that no one else was doing so. I watched in awe as I saw children in hijabs and well (to the best of their ability) ironed button-downed uniforms being taught how to design little orange robots. I watched seemingly precariously, as kids no younger than 12, were taught the rudimentary basics of coding via a very intriguing board game called Robot Turtle. The final objective of this game is for these children to gradually become comfortable handling algorithms and ease them into general rules of coding over time. The long term goal behind this is to groom the minds of the children to eventually become very comfortable with code. If this training pattern is successful, several kids at this center will be able to handle code before their 15th birthday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/techpreneurs/techpreneurs-03.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; title=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intrigued by what I had just witnessed, I spent some time with my new Borno family, organizing a mini competition with some of the children; where the first to fully set up a simple light bulb circuit board wins a round. After several rounds of laughter and high energy, as groups of kids squealed in the delight of playful rivalry while trying to outdo each other, I watched in silence and smiled at the realization of how the journey of ‘firsts’ could still be achieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I raised a high-five to myself (in my mind of course), at this light bulb moment: imagining a time when some of the next generations of Nigerian techpreneurs were going to emerge from. A new crop of data scientists and software engineers that understand the need for social investment innovation through technology based on their own personal experiences. A new class of information technology experts able to develop solutions from an honest place of empathy, having lived through the harsh realities of the absence of these basic threads of humanity often taken for granted because of how knitted they are into the fabric of what we see as everyday life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is these young ones learning the basics of computer coding from an early age, understanding how easily accessible education could become, and how the current unconventional approaches to learning could open up more minds to brilliant and truly impactful ideas. In the words of Wole Soyinka: “The phenomenon of creativity, we know, is closely related to the ability to yoke together separate, and even seemingly incompatible, matrices. The fruits of creativity taste best when it comes from the least likely places.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/techpreneurs/techpreneurs-04.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; title=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/techpreneurs/techpreneurs-05.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; title=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The e-learning solution designed at Softcom hopefully also contributes to this tale of firsts. From changing our perception of what free education could look like, redefining what it could possibly mean for mobile money to finally break into the mainstream payment culture in Nigeria (similar to what M-pesa has done in Kenya), to providing profitable make money on the go platforms for anyone irrespective of location across Nigeria. with the least KYC requirements possible, be able to make at least $150 on a monthly basis without ever meeting their employers face to face. I cannot wait to read the New York Times best seller story of how a group of Africans through their own journey from hopelessness to a tale of firsts, changed the world.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Social Impact" /><summary type="html">In 2006, a group of women from Northern India tired of the growing rate of unreported crimes against women, domestic abuse cases and a patriarchal system of oppression, decided that taking matters into their own hands was the only way the quest for justice and possible change could be shortened.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is Africa Ready for a Smart Speaker Revolution?</title><link href="https://softcom.ng/blog/smart-speaker/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is Africa Ready for a Smart Speaker Revolution?" /><published>2018-08-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-08-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://softcom.ng/blog/smart-speaker</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://softcom.ng/blog/smart-speaker/">&lt;p&gt;In 2011, Siri - originally intended as a standalone iOS app - was introduced alongside the iPhone 4S in its beta version. With the release of Siri, Apple device owners could now send texts, emails, make appointments, search the web, just by talking to their phones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seven years ago, this new technology seemed exclusive to Apple device owners, but that is no longer the case. Tech firms have since been on the line to provide humans with their interpretation of voice-powered AIs; from Microsoft’s Cortana and Amazon’s Alexa. This is mainly due to the rapid pace at which virtual digital assistants are being used, and the increasing number of people who agree it is a part of their everyday lives. After all, the Virtual Digital Assistant (VDA) worldwide market size is currently &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statista.com/statistics/589079/worldwide-virtual-digital-assistants-consumer-market/&quot; title=&quot;estimated&quot;&gt;estimated&lt;/a&gt; at $5.21bn, a number set to be slightly under 2 billion people when projecting the number of digital assistant users worldwide by 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these beg some questions: Are digital assistants really that intelligent? Are they really that effective in performing tasks? What is the future of Natural Language Processing (NLP) - the form of artificial intelligence that helps technology interpret human language - in analyzing, and parsing voice output, and improving the current level of AI? How, or rather when is this technology going to be available for the African market?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the nature of intelligence, especially in the context of artificial intelligence is still a fairly complex topic, digital assistants have been able to achieve some level of success. They are used to perform routine tasks like making and receiving phone calls, checking weather forecasts, traffic updates, news, and even make personalized recommendations. As we move towards a more sustainable development model in the innovation process, it is important to consistently re-imagine the future of digital interactive actions in a world of internet-enabled, connected intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider Google Home - the brand of smart speakers developed by Google. Released globally in 2017, Google says you “control your smart home with your voice”, and even that may be a sophisticated way of describing it. Google Home is basically the Google Assistant, built into a speaker, aimed at making life easier for its users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google isn’t the first company to offer smart speakers to consumers despite recent studies showing that there are now 14 million Google Home units in U.S. homes. For example, the Amazon Echo was launched in 2015 and commands nearly 72% market share of current U.S smart speaker owners, according to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://voicebot.ai/2018/03/08/amazon-echo-maintains-large-market-share-lead-u-s-smart-speaker-user-base/&quot; title=&quot;Voicebot Smart Speaker Consumer Adoption Report&quot;&gt;Voicebot Smart Speaker Consumer Adoption Report&lt;/a&gt; published this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, with the pricing of the Google Home, the company has revitalized the artificial intelligence race. Overtime, the plan is to catch up due to their appeal to a wider income class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;an-african-narrative&quot;&gt;An African Narrative&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already, today, quite a number of smart speaker applications are being imagined for various markets. This is especially important in a market like Africa’s, where its digitally competent consumer base is distributed across the different income levels. Google also offers its smart speaker in 3 variants: Google Home, Google Home Mini, and Google Home Max - possibly in recognition of the different set of users the product is being sold to. While the Home Max is built for high quality indoor and outdoor audio output, the Home Mini offers a lesser priced option that can be easily adopted by Africa’s middle and low income class. It’s important to note that the Home Mini doesn’t compromise on quality, and is also packed with all the features of the digital assistant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, there are several challenges in Africa that a tech gadget like this can help solve. Take for instance in the area of health, where patient adherence remains a primary healthcare problem in Africa. A smart speaker can be set to remind patients of clinic appointments, when it’s time to take their drugs, and provide health tips. The health of many patients with cardiovascular diseases - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2014/10/africas-top-health-challenge-cardiovascular-disease/381699/&quot; title=&quot;a top health challenge in Africa&quot;&gt;a top health challenge in Africa&lt;/a&gt; - can also be improved by monitoring their hearts’ conditions continuously in such a way that the patient’s doctor is aware of a pending heart attack even before they feel the pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another sector smart speaker can help transform is the farming industry - especially in rural Africa. The continent is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fao.org/fileadmin/templates/wsfs/docs/expert_paper/How_to_Feed_the_World_in_2050.pdf&quot; title=&quot;projected&quot;&gt;projected&lt;/a&gt; to be home to about 2 billion people by 2050, which means farm productivity must accelerate at a faster rate than the global average to avoid continued mass hunger. A smart speaker could provide periodic notifications to monitor crop growth and enable farmers monitor deviations from normal growth. While it’s still common for farmers to plant according to the phases of the moon, they can get real time weather updates so as to know the best periods to plant certain crops. This can potentially improve farm productivity and reduce input waste by using analytics to facilitate data-driven farming practices for small-scale farmers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/smart-speaker/smart-speaker-01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A couple of people&quot; title=&quot;Love in the Air&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even designing the product to use local accents and dialects for easier understanding and acceptance by the market. Talking about use cases, one of the more popular functions of the smart speaker is its ability to provide up-to-date traffic reports. Imagine if in this part of the world, we commenced the use of smart speakers notifying users of mishap on preferred routes, as it affected the user’s already predefined Google calendar. This feature is called “proactive assistance”- a notification system for things which Google Home finds useful to the user. With the unpredictable nature of road traffic in Africa’s major cities, information readily available right before leaving the home could be the difference between being on time for appointments, or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, all of these is still conceptual. Most companies that build smart speakers still haven’t made them available here, with the general perception of the continent as a potential market still largely prevalent. However, with the new problem-solving solutions they can bring to Africa in general, smart speakers can be the next flag bearers of a technological revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2018, with solutions like these on offer, it’s no wonder we are witnessing a remarkable rise in the pervasiveness of smart speakers; one that is nearly unprecedented in the history of consumer electronics. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalpublicmedia.com/smart-audio-report/latest-report/&quot; title=&quot;Smart Audio report&quot;&gt;Smart Audio report&lt;/a&gt; found that 3/4 of all smart speaker owners have owned their device for less than one year, with the balance (26%) falling into the first adopters category. Perhaps there’s a current awareness of the multi-functional usefulness of these gadgets, the potential of connected devices, and the reasonable price at which they are offered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s crucial to note that the evolution of technology like smart speakers stem from a desire to be connected consistently to the Internet - which is true everywhere in the world. As a result of this, “The Internet of Things” (IoT) - a term used to describe the connection of everything from gadgets to ordinary objects, to the Internet, has become a piece of our culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it may not seem like the urgent need of the hour in Africa, understanding the capabilities of these devices make them appealing. With home automation and IoT poised to grow in the future, a piece of technology that make our lives easier is not a hard sell. The Google Home also largely delivers on primarily being an excellent digital assistant: it answers personalized questions, can access several internet services, and make hands-free phone calls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, the evolution of Wi-Fi-enabled smart devices means we have to deal with communicating with them. This means we can have conversations with them, the same way we talk to one another when we need to get things done. An effect of the Internet of Things is that smartphones will become not only our portal into this interconnected ecosystem, but a control to our lives: enabling access to information on the go, and completion of automated tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With more features including “visual responses” and a willingness to adapt their products and services for the non-American user, the Google Home has the potential of being the revolutionary device that changes the perception of IoT in Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like the earlier trends of mobile phones, laptops - and most recently wearable tech - the current rate of usage won’t remain low forever. In the not too distant future, Africans will be talking to home assistants that not only help with task-oriented commands, but also goal-oriented ones.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="AI" /><summary type="html">Are digital assistants really that intelligent? Are they really that effective in performing tasks? What is the future of Natural Language Processing (NLP) - the form of artificial intelligence that helps technology interpret human language - in analyzing, and parsing voice output, and improving the current level of AI?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How Africa Is Leveraging Tech To Drive Social Impact Programmes</title><link href="https://softcom.ng/blog/how-africa-is-leveraging-tech/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Africa Is Leveraging Tech To Drive Social Impact Programmes" /><published>2018-07-31T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-07-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://softcom.ng/blog/how-africa-is-leveraging-tech</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://softcom.ng/blog/how-africa-is-leveraging-tech/">&lt;p&gt;Over the past few years in Africa, there’s been a concerted effort towards creating social impact initiatives by the government, corporate organizations and even international non-government organizations (NGOs) in an attempt to reduce poverty and deliver a better standard of living for disadvantaged people and communities. With 47% of the African population battling extreme poverty, economic development policies targeted at improving the lives of the less privileged in the society have become much more important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, research suggests that things are not getting better as the level of poverty and marginalization appear to be on the increase in the continent. Africa remains by far the poorest continent on the planet — 28 of the world’s poorest countries are African.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several issues accompany the implementation of government policies, nevertheless, economic growth and development are addressed through the deployment of these policies. Issues such as inequality, economic diversification, unemployment, poverty, human capital deficit, rural development, are majorly solved through social impact programs. This makes the policymaking process as well as implementation — withstanding its challenges — highly imperative. On the whole, African social impact programs have continued to be held back by structural weaknesses — especially in the area of financial mobilization — that haven’t yet been tackled adequately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While much has been said about Africa’s struggle with corrupt leaders, and the role they play in the failure of these programs, there have been some success stories nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On March 18 2016, South Africa’s West Cape Province Departments of Social Development and Health committed 25 million rand ($1.62 million) to funding three social impact bonds (SIBs) for maternal and early childhood outcomes. It was the first ever funding committed by a middle-income government for an SIB, making South Africa’s choice to pioneer this new path encouraging. Over a period of three years, the goal has been to use “state funding to create a blended outcomes fund, which may prove more efficient than when non-profit organizations raise grant funding to augment inadequate government subsidies”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example is Mali’s Agricultural Competitiveness and Diversification Project (ACDP), implemented by the Malian Ministry of Agriculture aimed at poverty reduction and increase in rural incomes. The program has helped expand the market for mango and other crops, as well as build good business practices within the country’s agricultural sector. This has been achieved with some stakeholders — from farmers to harvesters to collectors to processors and exporters — all benefitting from the expansion in trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past 20 years however, the continent has recorded huge success in the mobile segment of Information and Communication Technologies (ICTs). Mobile networks have covered over 90% of Africa’s urban population, and Sub-Sahara has the highest ratio of mobile to telephone subscribers of any region in the world. There’s also been an increased awareness surrounding the central importance of education to development. The world today is a knowledge-based economy and the benefits accruable from the blurring geographical boundaries can only be maximised by nations with a highly skilled and educated labour force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Affordable education and easy access to information technology tools, thus, represents a means to foster economic development, as well as improve levels of education, especially in African countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/africa-leveraging-tech/africa-leveraging-tech-01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A couple of people&quot; title=&quot;Love in the Air&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nigeria’s N-Power
A social development program that combines technology and education is the N-Power program, launched by the current Nigerian government and chaired by Vice President, Yemi Osinbajo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;N-Power is a government initiative aimed at empowering Nigerian youths while achieving inclusion and productivity through large-scale skill development. It aims to improve the lives of 500,000 individuals over a two-year period, training them in programs that range from Health and Tax (N-Power Health and Tax) to Agriculture and Education (N-Power Agro and N-Power Teach).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eighteen months into the program, beneficiaries are expected to have created sustainable means of generating income at the nuclear and intra-community level given the access to skills and development courses provided via the e-learning platform that the program offers and the stipend provided by the government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it’s tempting to attribute the success of N-Power to the efficiency of its co-ordinators, an appreciation for the management of its IT infrastructure starts to emerge on a deeper glance; especially considering that the program in itself relies heavily on the use of ICTs. In offering beneficiaries an e-learning mobile tablet equipped with both offline and online study materials, the N-Power initiative is highly dependent on the technology that powers these devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this vein, the partnership between the federal government and Softcom, a private tech solutions company, highlights the best of what can be achieved when the public and private sector collaborates to implement policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Softcom Limited, we pride ourselves on delivering tech-based solutions to enable social and economic impact for the African continent. With industry expertise in different sectors, they’ve been able to connect individuals with meaningful innovations, from delivering the educational aspect of the N-Power platform on e-tablets to developing a truly inclusive FinTech solution. Softcom also engage in targeted community social responsibility campaigns built around tech, and aimed at impacting communities from the grassroots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The progressive biases looking for innovative ways to design and implement social impact programs becomes a model for African nations; understanding how and why economic recovery efforts work in other countries and adapting it for their own environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the perception of Africa as a struggling continent is to be changed, open regional economic collaboration and integration will be important to truly achieving economic diversification and inclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building solutions that work and delivering them in a country like Nigeria — with its myriad complexity — is a gargantuan task. With a population size that easily doubles that of over 70% of all African nations, it isn’t far-fetched to believe that the success of a development program in Nigeria could translate to success in most African countries.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Social Impact" /><summary type="html">Affordable education and easy access to information technology tools, represents a means to foster economic development, as well as improve levels of education, especially in African countries.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Choosing Home Series 2: Toluyemi talks about being a Woman in Tech</title><link href="https://softcom.ng/blog/choosing-home-series-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Choosing Home Series 2: Toluyemi talks about being a Woman in Tech" /><published>2018-07-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-07-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://softcom.ng/blog/choosing-home-series-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://softcom.ng/blog/choosing-home-series-2/">&lt;p&gt;As the perception continues to change on Africa’s one-dimensional portrayal as a struggling continent, the tide of brain drain from developing to developed nations is reducing as a growing number of highly skilled and educated Nigerians, Ghanaians, Somalians etc. flock back to their countries of birth after some time away. They left, either as children with their immigrant parents or for study and early career opportunities. They return, in search of an identity, of bigger opportunities, to seek their roots, and determined to make a change. The countries they come back to are certainly the winners in this affair, as these are typically the very best and brightest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/choosing-home-series-2/choosing-home-series-01.png&quot; alt=&quot;A couple of people&quot; title=&quot;Love in the Air&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toluyemi Nathaniel remembers when she had the awakening moment of making the decision to return home to Nigeria. It was close to the end of her 2-year stay in China studying for a Master’s Degree in International Economics and Business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For me, I just had to come back. I love Nigeria and I can’t imagine being somewhere else for so long without itching to return”, started a sprightly Tolu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“All I kept thinking of was how much can I change over there? I just feel sometimes, it’s more difficult to change things you haven’t experienced. Everyone that has made a change in this country are people that lived through the Nigerian story and made up their mind to change things when given the opportunity. I decided to join that group.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In substantiating her refreshing sense of duty towards her country, Tolu reveals that she wasn’t forced to return because her program was over — a common occurrence in some cases — but that she actually did have the chance to further her education there but declined to. It’s an obligation to national service that’s established subtly in all of how she talks about her return, but that can be missed from the affectionate way with which she describes China and the period of her stay there. Curious to understand how she found herself in China in the first place, I asked about the reasoning behind the decision to leave for that particular country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: Staying in a country with a different cultural background to what one is used to can be a bit tough, and while Nigerians travel to a lot of countries around the world, deciding to live in a country like China still sticks out as peculiar. Was it your choice to go to China or was it out of your control?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tolu:&lt;/strong&gt; Yes, deciding to go there was 100% my choice. It was actually my first time out of the country, but I didn’t want something familiar, which is what the UK or America would’ve been for me. In fact, immediately after I got there, there was this episode at the airport where there was a mix up with me reclaiming my luggage. Officials gathered trying to solve the problem, but they were all speaking Chinese, which I didn’t understand at the time. This didn’t frighten me, but instead did the opposite; I was, in fact, more interested to understand the language. In its own way for me, it was about fulfilling a sense of adventure I’d long craved. I’m a thrill seeker at heart, so China was a place I really looked forward to living in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/choosing-home-series-2/choosing-home-series-03.png&quot; alt=&quot;A couple of people&quot; title=&quot;Love in the Air&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her take on a seeming over-familiarization of foreigners with Western culture is valid in the growing sense that with its global connection, European culture has grown with an all-inclusive urge to adopt, adapt, and ultimately influence other cultural trends around the world. In comparison to a country with a rich cultural history and background still waiting to be explored by most, it’s understandable why the Asian country will be a better pick to experience an original cultural adventure. It’s all well and good, however, the intricacies of living as a minority in the most populated nation on earth remains a reality that can’t be written off. Last year, Quartz published a comprehensive report on a growing fear in some parts of China of a “black invasion bringing drugs and crime” due to the increasing number of African migrants. I talked to Tolu about what it’s like living as a black person in a foreign country, aware of recent victories for nationalist sentiments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: Can you share with us what it’s like studying and living in China as a young black Nigerian woman?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tolu:&lt;/strong&gt; That can honestly be a bit tricky to navigate because the Chinese aren’t used to seeing black people. They are almost fascinated when they see one, and still do things like rubbing a black person’s skin, asking if it is ‘dirt’. I’ve had a few people do that to me. Sometimes, they just stare at you because they’ve never seen someone like that before. In my case I was fortunate because Tianjin (where she stayed) has one of the highest percentages when it comes to the number of different national ethnicities. I met other Africans, and some of my classmates were in fact black. There are blatant cases like when cars don’t wait to pick you up, or when I was told to “sound American” at an interview trying to get a job as an English tutor on campus. So living there as an African woman, there’s this contention of you constantly trying to decide if it’s racism or simply ignorance which I guess is the same for most black people there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overt displays of racism from locals can be too much to handle for some living in the diaspora. For these people, the danger of being targeted by racial violence can be the deal breaker between settling and returning home. Tolu, however, insists that she doesn’t regret her decision to move there, and says she’s gained a new perspective on some issues because of some of her encounters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There’s a lot of how things are done over there that will be strange to us. There are things we can copy and a couple of things we shouldn’t copy. It’s a fascinating array of differences in culture and practice that if a balance can be found, a lot of problems will be solved. But the process of finding that balance comes with a firsthand participation in a challenging change to one’s conventions and ideas of the world.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case for diaspora-return driven development in Nigeria is compelling, and the advantages cannot be denied. Returnees come to represent a bridge of the ever-widening knowledge gap, finding solutions to knotty problems with more sophisticated approaches due to an experience of both worlds. With Nigeria’s labour force on a perpetual rise — &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vanguardngr.com/2017/12/nigerias-labour-force-increases-85m-q3-nbs/&quot; title=&quot;Love in the Air&quot;&gt;National Bureau of Statistics&lt;/a&gt; says it increased from 83.9m in Q2, 2017 to 85.1m in Q3, 2017 — the majority of the population being dominated by people who’ve gained some know-how in important areas of technology and systems will be key in furthering economic progress in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For her own part, Tolu works as an Admin and Procurement Associate at Softcom Ltd, a company which has the pungent line of “Engineering to enhance the way we live, learn and work in Africa” as part of its Solutions Portfolio. While the parallels are present, the difference in her educational background in Economics and Business and her current job role is still conspicuous. I tried to find out about how she found herself in this line of work, what the role entails, and what a typical day at work is like for her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: Can you explain a bit more about your role? What does working in Procurement/Operations mean in the tech world?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A:&lt;/strong&gt; Like I said earlier, I had the opportunity to start my PhD even after getting back to Nigeria but I declined because I wanted to work. When job opportunities in Business weren’t forthcoming, I took on the challenge of working in Admin &amp;amp; Procurement, a role I wasn’t so familiar with prior to that point. But it’s been amazing because I have learnt so much on the job and now I’m just working towards being the best I can be at it. In Admin, the objective is to ensure there is a smooth operation of activities in the office. Responsibilities can range from automating the monitoring of various activities and contracts to coordination and management of administrative issues like hygiene &amp;amp; welfare. Generally, admin is more concerned with making the work environment much more conducive to boost productivity levels. As a Procurement Associate, I’m equally tasked with being responsible for all the purchases at Softcom. In a tech company, this includes project-specific materials which involves negotiating with external vendors to secure advantageous terms. So in a way, my background in business has come in handy in executing some of my current job requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While trying to understand the complicated landscape of Nigeria’s job market, a bit of background context is required. The country is included among the 10 fastest growing markets in the world, but still faces the problem of an overcrowded labour market that’s made gainful employment a premium in recent years. Tech companies like Softcom meanwhile have taken advantage of the explosion of Nigeria’s digital economy, seeing the sector as an avenue to tap into a rapidly urbanizing population of about 80 million people, whilst providing solutions to issues and sustainable employment to citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important point of note is that Tolu talks about how the Nigerian job market remains a slippery slope to navigate for women, especially in tech. Despite extolling Softcom’svalue of commitment to diversity, she is under no illusions and is affirmatory when she answers “I honestly don’t think we are that much” to my question about how many women she thinks exists in tech spaces these days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gender disparity isn’t peculiar to the tech sector, but stats point to a decline in the percentage of women in computing-related occupations since 1991. It’s a problem felt across board, as women in tech still face significant barriers in the workplace; from a shortage of women role models to inequitable pay gap, to persistent gender bias that nearly 90% of them say they have experienced. I got a few of Tolu’s thoughts on what she thinks the future holds for women in tech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: How do you think we as a country can ensure there is more equitable pay across the board, how we get more women into senior level and executive positions, how we fight unconscious bias at all levels of a tech organization?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tolu:&lt;/strong&gt; I think we first of all need to create a nationwide awareness to change some long-held backward cultural beliefs about women, including that men are naturally more talented than women when it comes to tech. It starts when we are kids; I’d love to see more little girls in computer classes. They don’t have to all be doctors, lawyers, and engineers. An emphasis should also be placed on merit-based appointments. At Softcom, it doesn’t matter if you are male or female, if you bring value to the company, you’ll sit at the table. So it should be that it is one’s substance — not gender — that’s considered when deciding on delegating executive roles. The promotion of and donations to organizations dedicated to the cause of making workplaces as diverse as possible is also important in solving bias issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tolu imagines a bright future for women in tech and even for the industry at large. There’s a confidence in the idea that with the advancement of technology in coming years, there will be more job openings in tech. However, such is the optimism from new returnees that it can sometimes almost be misconstrued as wishful thinking. When asked about her message for those still struggling with the decision to come back home, she talks about “sobering realities” but insists there are revolutionary solutions waiting to be applied in several spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I can’t lie, it’s a bit tough. You can never be prepared for some things. The heat was almost unbearable for me initially. I also had a bad bout with cholera off the first glass of water I drank. So yes it can be rough but being strong and focusing on the motive for coming back keeps me going. For me, that is contributing daily towards being an agent of positive change in my country. I also have to add that for a young black woman, it can be extra difficult. The career ladder doesn’t favour us already but what I see it as are that these are the very dynamics that make the prospect of change appealing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no doubting the impact of diaspora returnees like Tolu and their contributions to the national effort of growth and development. The Nigerian government must develop credible strategies for progress in many of the areas that lead these people to leave their home countries in the first place. For those who have not decided to return home, they will never be motivated to contribute their energies to a national cause unless the government makes an effort at creating the type of country they would like to return to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Returning to the country with a strategic approach should also be encouraged among the returnees. Appreciating that there are visceral realities that come with living in Nigeria is key, but balancing that with the right, tolerant and optimistic attitude is important for their relocation to be successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above all, there should be a general understanding that there’s never been a better time than now for the application of great and progressive ideas in the country. In an emerging economy with strong numbers, opportunities abound that can shift the course of the nation onto a progressive path. Tolu recognizes the importance of opportunities when she talked about lessons she’s learnt over the past 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/choosing-home-series-2/choosing-home-series-03.png&quot; alt=&quot;Toluyemi Nathaniel&quot; title=&quot;Love in the Air&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If I was to write a letter to my younger self, it will be to take opportunities as they come. A Colombian friend in China used to tell me that “If you don’t taste the food, how do you know if you’ll like it?” A life lesson for me has really been that taking advantage of opportunities can unexpectedly change a lot in a short space of time.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="African Diaspora" /><category term="Women In Tech" /><summary type="html">The case for diaspora returnees and their contribution towards development is compelling. In the 2nd part of our Choosing Home series, Tolu Nathaniel talks about her experience in China and how she contributes to making an impact via Softcom.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Choosing Home: Young Nigerians Retracing Their Steps One Pace At a Time</title><link href="https://softcom.ng/blog/choosing-home/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Choosing Home: Young Nigerians Retracing Their Steps One Pace At a Time" /><published>2018-05-19T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-05-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://softcom.ng/blog/choosing-home</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://softcom.ng/blog/choosing-home/">&lt;p&gt;While marking Nigeria in the Diaspora day in 2015, Nigeria’s Foreign Affairs Minister at the time, Mrs. Ngozi Okonjo-Iweala observed that remittances by Nigerians in the Diaspora are in the region of $4 billion yearly. This will frankly be a staggering amount until you consider that just last year, the Senior Special Assistant to the President on Foreign Affairs and The Diaspora, Mrs Abike Dabiri-Erewa announced that about 15 million Nigerians live in the Diaspora.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These numbers should be rightly considered whopping sums that could — if properly applied — boost the economy of any developing country. However, there’s an increasingly new crop of returning Nigerians that are looking at making that impact on the upward curve of the economy with the application of their skills in the labour market, while simultaneously contributing to help build the Nigeria of their dreams. Data on the actual numbers of returnees is still lacking, but it is broadly acknowledged, based on the increasing visibility of the diaspora in society, that there has been a steady increase in returns in the past few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The raw energy of youth, a millennial generation, and the recent rise of many technology-powered companies in Nigeria are the common denominators present here. These companies try to address the country’s problems with their unique solutions. One of them that works at such a company is Ope Adeyemi, a Solutions Architect at Softcom Nigeria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not so surprisingly, Ope just returned last year after an almost 2-year stay in the United Kingdom during which he studied for a Master’s Degree in Control &amp;amp; Systems Engineering. The urge to bridge a knowledge gap and experience other cultures were on his mind when he left, but because his decision to willingly return will no doubt have come as a surprise to some Nigerians, I ask him about his thoughts on his return to the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: You’ve just moved back to the country in a move that will come as a surprise to majority of Nigerians active in the labour market, as there are a lot willing to at least try the opportunities they believe are more available abroad. Can you share the main motivation behind your decision to move back to the country?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ope: I got sponsored for a Masters Degree Program by a government body called Petroleum Technology Development Fund (PTDF). It was a very few of us picked out of a thousand of applicants after an exam. It was supposed to be a kind of implicit agreement between us and the government, to transfer the knowledge we gain the during the duration of the program back into the country. PTDF, however, wanted to make it official, so they demanded we sign a bond. Some objected to this initially, but for me, the question has always been that if the government is willing to invest about ₦50m on you, why wouldn’t you want to exchange that for an opportunity to apply some of those skills in contributing to the development of the country? For me even before going there, I took it is an obligation to come back and help in my way.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a degree of truth to the almost mythologized belief that Nigerians aren’t time conscious, but a factor for that might genuinely be — in the case of Lagos — due to the notorious traffic congestion the city’s infamous for. Lagos, Nigeria’s popular former capital, is its most populous state; which makes the astronomical high amount of internal revenue it generates on its own (the state governor puts Total Revenue Generated for 2017 at ₦503.7bn) not so surprising. Lagos is expected to gain from policy reforms focused on improving the support for private firms and has been touted to become the 2nd largest African city by Gross Domestic Product (GDP) according to an Oxford Economics report. By 2050, experts foresee that the country’s population is set to rocket to 397 million. While the population boom will impact the whole country, nowhere will it be more profound than in Lagos, putting it on the level of the world’s megacities but with less infrastructure than any other large cities of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, this increases pressure on the city’s job sector and accounts for the notoriously difficult to navigate setup of the Lagos labour market. Talking about getting situated and finding one’s feet in such a landscape, Ope reveals that in his own case, he had gotten the job at Softcom before he travellsed, and was still fortunate enough to be absorbed back into the fold on his return.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It has allowed me to continue my work with a sense of continuity and purpose that I probably wouldn’t have gotten anywhere else. The process of having the most qualified candidates get the jobs they deserve still needs a bit of fine-tuning, but I’m glad I get to work in the ICT industry because yes I love tech, but I’ve always primarily wondered how technology can help provide solutions to some long-standing problems.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2016, Nigeria recorded an all-time high contribution of 12.6% by ICT to its Gross Domestic Product and just last year, the Nigerian Communications Commission (NCC) announced that the quarterly contribution of ICT to the GDP has increased to ₦1.6trn from ₦1.4trn. This recent rise in the importance of ICT as a major contributor to the success of Nigeria’s economic diversification plan has birthed companies like Softcom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/choosing-home/choosing-home-01.png&quot; alt=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; title=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi sharing his job description at Softcom Limited.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Softcom tags themselves as “a thinking company” and their solutions portfolio includes specialization in “creating and directing the implementation of strategic road maps that place organizations at the cusp of technology”. Ope agrees that Nigeria’s Information and Communication Technology industry can be a major factor in finally transitioning Nigeria’s economy from being less reliant on oil, but understanding exactly how might still be vague to a lot. I ask him about how his work at Softcom is helping to improve ICT’s position as a major tool for socio-economic development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: What are some of the more challenging but ultimately rewarding projects you’ve had an opportunity to take part in as a member of the staff at Softcom?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ope: I think they are 2 different things: challenging and impactful. A project might be challenging without being necessarily impactful, but I’m more interested in the latter. One of such projects was the MTN Trade Visibility Project. Basically, it was about the client needing an analysis on exactly which locations to prioritize their distribution of merchandize materials like chairs and banners among their retailers. The problem was that they weren’t getting any data needed for that. What we did at Softcom was to come up with a Trade Visibility analysis which entailed going around the country to gather information on MTN’s visibility against its competitors in certain areas. What this does is allow the client to optimally allocate resources to places where their presence is low as compared to competitors. The outcome of this project has driven down their expense by about 70%, which is objectively a whole lot. In this case, the project was challenging and very impactful at the same time.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The move of the world towards becoming a technology-driven society means the future of Information and Communications Technology is very promising in Nigeria. The ease of the networking process that involves brands and individuals is being constantly reimagined almost daily especially in the age of social media. A lot more people are also being made more aware of the changes good technology solutions can bring to present-day challenges in agriculture, health, education, banking and finance, and other areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Nigeria, this sense of a technology revolution and the progressive pace at which it’s currently growing makes the decision for people like Ope to return from the overseas and try to carve their way, not so far-fetched. On his work at Softcom aligning with the motivation behind his return to the country, he talks about how the ICT industry was the most obvious fit for the application of the knowledge he gained abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I studied Control &amp;amp; Systems Engineering for my Masters Program and while we could talk about the Oil &amp;amp; Gas industry, I had already been exposed in the tech industry prior to leaving, so it felt like a natural decision to come back and continue. Softcom’s different departments mean that the members of staff have ideas of how what they do aligns with their own individual goals. I currently work in a department called Client Services where I work as a Solutions Architect. Some of the things I do involves IT Solutions Designing, Business Development, and Brand Management. However, I specifically chose to come back to this role because I feel like while building the tech is the easy part, building the business around the tech is tricky.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The concept of Business Development has always interested me so this is my way of exploring the processes behind developing and implementing growth opportunities within and between organizations.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/choosing-home/choosing-home-02.png&quot; alt=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi discussing why he came back to Nigeria.&quot; title=&quot;Opeyemi Adeyemi discussing why he came back to Nigeria.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea behind Nigerians in the Diaspora, now established as a euphemism for Nigerians living outside the country, particularly in Europe and America, is fascinating. Nevertheless, lanes should be opened for youths skilled or educated in the West to return and contribute towards the process of achieving real growth in the country. The drive and resourcefulness of people like Ope in different sectors of the country is important as Nigeria moves towards becoming a globally competitive nation. Questions surrounding how experience gained by these Nigerians can be harnessed for the direct benefit of the country needs to be asked, alongside awareness campaigns spreading word of the opportunities that are beginning to spring up in the country.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="African Diaspora" /><summary type="html">The idea behind Nigerians in the Diaspora, now established as a euphemism for Nigerians living outside the country, particularly in Europe and America, is fascinating. Read about the reason behind Ope Adeyemi’s decision to return to Nigeria, after an almost 2-year stay in the United Kingdom.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Facial Recognition: What It Is and How Organisations Can Benefit</title><link href="https://softcom.ng/blog/facial-recognition/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Facial Recognition: What It Is and How Organisations Can Benefit" /><published>2018-04-13T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-04-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://softcom.ng/blog/facial-recognition</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://softcom.ng/blog/facial-recognition/">&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, we are observing more cameras in our society. They are present in quite a lot of places: streets, supermarkets, churches, mosques and many other public places across Nigeria. The primary aim of their presence is most of the time related to surveillance and security management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Facial recognition being one of the blow-the-trumpet features to come to smart devices and with the IPhone X gaining quite some popularity amongst phone users in Nigeria, FR technology is definitely here to positively disrupt the process of achieving identity management and even payment in the Nigerian fin-tech space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-does-fr-actually-work&quot;&gt;How Does FR Actually work?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FR algorithms simply extract facial information from a person’s face and analyses these features against a set of rules previously set up within the algorithm. The most popular face recognition method (Three-Dimensional Recognition) uses 3D sensors to determine certain facial information — face structure, chin, nose and eye sockets and compares it against a previously saved copy of the image on a phone or a database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/facial-recognition/facial-recognition-01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Placeholder&quot; title=&quot;Placeholder&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, Apple’s Face ID on the iPhone X “uses a ‘TrueDepth’ camera setup, which blasts your face with more than 30,000 infrared dots and scans your face in 3D. A portion of the A11 Bionic chip’s neural engine transforms the depth map and infrared image into a mathematical representation and compares that representation to the enrolled facial data.” This method helps the smartphone make a quick decision on if the person holding the phone to his or her face truly owns the phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Access Management:&lt;/strong&gt; With facial recognition, organizations can easily manage entrance and exit at their business locations, achieve optimum staff identity management, attendance monitoring and surveillance on business premises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;your-cameras-are-becoming-part-of-your-marketing-team&quot;&gt;Your cameras are becoming part of your Marketing Team&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Large retail businesses can access insightful customer information by capturing the facial data of customers that visit their stores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Analytics:&lt;/strong&gt; For example, a shopper goes to ShopRite, Maryland Mall and makes several purchases of a specific brand of chocolate over the course of 1 month. ShopRite can store these vital biometric information which may give quite some insight into a customer’s in-store purchasing behaviour, demographics, psychographics etc. With access to this type of data, businesses can make more informed marketing decisions like simply offering him discount on many purchases of his favourite chocolate or presenting him with loyalty schemes etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/facial-recognition/facial-recognition-02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Placeholder&quot; title=&quot;Placeholder&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identity Management:&lt;/strong&gt; Examination bodies like UTME, IELTS and TOEFL can also utilize facial recognition in managing various attendees’ identity in physical or online examinations. FR can also be used in checking travelers at airports and boarding stations.In the United States, the Transportation Security Administration (TSA) recently launched a facial check-in feature at airports.This was piloted a few weeks ago at the Los Angeles LAX airport. With this feature, travelers can literally walk the check-in aisle and get checked-in via facial recognition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between January and September 2017, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.premiumtimesng.com/business/business-news/253834-nigerian-airports-record-9-2-million-passengers-140552-aircraft-movement-nine-months.html&quot; title=&quot;Placeholder&quot;&gt;Nigeria’s airports&lt;/a&gt; recorded 9.2 million flights in 140,552 aircraft movements . With this high amount of travellers flying within and outside Nigeria, an investment in FR technology by Nigeria’s NCAA, FAAN will ensure a seamless check-in and boarding process at all airports in Nigeria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;are-we-amped-about-what-were-building-yes&quot;&gt;Are We Amped About What We’re Building? Yes!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building solutions that add value to people and businesses is an important part of the things we do at Softcom. In the coming weeks, we’ll be launching one of our fin-tech products aimed at helping our potential users achieve seamless payments via their telephone numbers and more importantly approving payments via facial recognition. With the FR algorithm, users can easily achieve payments by simply placing their mobile devices against their faces to authorize payments at a brick and mortar shopping store or online when.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="AI" /><summary type="html">With facial recognition being one of the blow-the-trumpet features to come to smart devices, FR technology is definitely here to positively disrupt the process of achieving identity management and even payment in the Nigerian Fin-Tech space.</summary></entry></feed>